hello and welcome this is active guest
stream 64.1 it's November 29th 2023
we're here with Elliot Murphy returning
guest and we'll be talking about this
paper rose a neurocomputational
architecture for syntax so for
introduction and describing how today's
stream's going to go Elliot thank you
for joining to you all right thanks so
much Daniel uh yeah I work at the uh UT
Health in Houston in Texas in an
epilepsy uh monitoring unit where we use
interc
cranial um recordings to maap language
in patients with epilepsy and but today
I want to present something a little bit
more theoretical a little bit more kind
of philosophical almost um this is a new
paper that's just come out in the
Journal of neural Linguistics and I
thought it' be good for me um just to
kind of walk through the paper step by
step uh give some motivation give some
description destion give some kind of
outline of of the general kind of
framing for the paper so the framework
for this paper is trying to propose a
general model for how to research
language using inter cranial recordings
um it's basically kind of move Beyond
research that comes from other kinds of
extracranial Imaging methods um and it's
trying to really figure out what is the
most appropriate level of description in
terms of neural complexity for specific
aspects of language so there's many
different parts of language as We Know
uh language has words it has sounds you
know it has you can read language you
can you can sign it you can construct
meaning um you can do all sorts of
things but the real kind of question for
me is um at what level of neural
complexity um and therefore at what
level of appropriate recording
resolution based on what tools you have
available uh is going to be uh providing
you with the most reliable signatures of
particular levels of of structure so um
uh in this model ter the rose model I
invoke representations operations
structures and encoding and I'll
introduce them step by step um and so
for the purposes of of this kind of
introduction um I'm just going to kind
of outline what those General kind of
Frameworks are but to begin um the most
kind of basic assumption that we have
about language in terms of like the
finding some Linguistics so the study of
language like the scientific study of
language one of the really basic
introductions that you find in every
introductory textbook is that um
linguists have kind of arrived at the
conclusion that the human mind brain
applies a set of rules to recursively
combine linguistic units into larger
objects which deres an unbounded array
of hierarchically structured Expressions
uh with humans INF fairing sentence
meaning based on syntactic configuration
now that's a lot of jargon but
essentially what that means is when you
um hear a linear sequence of words like
uh you know we watched a movie with Jim
kry you can pass that not simply as like
beads on a string you can pass it in two
ways depending on how you chunk the
individual phrases together and how you
establish relations between the
different elements so for example you
know we watched the movie with McCary
can mean that you watched um you know
Eternal Sunshine of spot's mind or it
can mean that you're sat there next to
Jim Carrey watching you know uh the new
Napoleon film for example so there's
there's kind of ambiguity there but the
ambiguity arises due to structural
configurations so that that's kind of
how you uh rearrange the sentences kind
of in your head internally and that is
obviously a process that's independent
immediately from sensory motor either
Transformations or experience or speech
or sound or orthography so these are
very abstract processes and they're
clearly mental processes they're not
processes of the visual system they're
not processes of the auditory system
they're clearly uh hod mental
computations so what that phrase
unbounded array of hierarchic excted
Expressions means is it just means that
humans have this generative capacity and
people like car Kristen and chsky talk
about generativity quite a lot what
basically means is the ability to just
do exactly what I'm doing right now use
a finite set of elements so lexical
items or you know memorize words and
then recombine them again again again in
really novel combinations such that you
can say sentences that have you know
never been said before in you know the
totality of human existence um but which
are immediately assigned a meaning you
don't have to think too hard about what
meanings are usually unless you're
reading you know finegan weight um for
example so uh typically this is a
reflective process so it's automatic
it's quick uh the brain resolves this uh
very well um without much effort without
much entic cost as well and so the
question is how does the brain do this
um so you know uh additional point to
make here is that this capacity for
hierarchical occasion has also been
linked to human specific cognitive
superiority so that's a more General
background here so people like Stander
how and what will they've long stressed
that this facility for constructing
hierarchically organized uh linguistic
structures um is really potentially a
human specific function and that's a
very long and and you know
uh it's a long and difficult topic to
get to get into so I'll put it to one
side but it's an interesting topic to to
explore the possibility that this
whatever this process is it might in
fact be unique to
humans um so in the theoretical domain U
turning to neurobiology an emerging
consensus in Neuroscience is that
complex behavior and cognition rely on
coordinated interactions between brain
regions with phase synchronization being
a major candidate for a mechanism
implementing this coordination by gating
information Transmission in the brain
and but unlike for models of attention
and working memory there's currently an
absence of hillory phase coding in
models of natural language so what does
that mean uh so in uh the neurobiology
of attention and working memory there's
been a lot of really exciting accounts
by people like El Miller O enen uh and a
lot of other people uh trying to explore
the relationship between neural
synchronization metrics and some kind of
isomorphic kind of relationship to some
property of an either an endogenous
computation like a working memory
process or some kind of property of the
environment that you're kind of you know
passing in real time and but in language
the best we have just to boil it down
very very generally the best we have at
the moment in language is basically what
called cartographic models so that's
kind of localizationist models in the
brain so we have a decent idea thanks to
the really brilliant work by people like
Greg Hickock and Willam matchin and Anga
friederich and ning and David poel and
really an you know a really incredible
roster of people from the last few
decades who very carefully maed out
which specific brain regions seem to be
sensitive to different types of of
linguistic structure so lexicality
meaning you know the meaning of a word
um syntax the the generation of a
sentence structure or phrase structure
semantics the meaning of words phology
and so on but what we really have right
now is just a kind of map so we have a
map of the brain that you can pull up on
Google and you can Google you know
language syntax brain and you'll get a
decent uh you know rough architecture of
which parts of the brain seem to be
sensitive to different parts of language
but the the main reason why I wrote this
paper is because that's of essential you
know mapping out the terrain is
obviously essential but the next step
and people from working memory Vision
attention they they did this you know a
while ago the next step is therefore to
transition to a kind of how question
which is which neural mechanisms are
involved in language so rather than
simply saying these are the brain
regions involved we have to then say
okay these are the brain regions but
what is the brain doing right like what
operations are is it's performing at
what level of neural complexity um is it
sensitive so just because this part of
the brain is
sensitive we don't really know in what
way it's sensitive like how is what what
what type of neural processes is it
actually recruiting to yield that
sensitivity and what does that
sensitivity really look like outside of
B fluctuations or you know High gamma
amplitude increases and and other kind
of typical measurements so that's in the
theoretical domain in the empirical
domain invasive interc cranial
recordings have recently mapped out some
of the feature space associated with how
much phological information can be
transmitted by different neural
mechanisms and some citations they you
to look at but within the domains of
syntax and semantics there's been less
clear progress and the reason for that
is pretty obvious and phology sound
auditory processing you know the kind of
finite feature space involved in opticor
processes uh that's a very non-trivial
you know field to explore but it has
been mapped out very clearly because the
you know processes are kind of less
abstract more well agreed upon uh more
transparent they involve more clear uh
sensory motor Transformations and things
that you can detect very clearly with
very nice clear signatures in uh in
different types of neural States state
space State space or in fact different
regions of the brain um and these are
also things that you can distri disrupt
very easily so it's very easy to disrupt
phological processing we know we know
which parts of the brains uh which parts
of Cortex is disrupted but it's less
clear how you specifically disrupt
things like syntax and sematics you can
knock out you know language
comprehension in general just all of
language comprehension you can knock out
and disrupt um certain aspects of
working memory performance but when it
comes to knocking out you know
disrupting the brain's ability to
specifically process syntactic or
semantic information
that's been very difficult and there's
only been a few papers on that which I
site in this paper over the last couple
years but it's been it's very difficult
to really try and you know provide
causal information causal evidence to
try and really stimulate I stimulate the
brain in the o or to find you know uh
lesion patients who've had a stroke and
who exhibit extremely specific Niche you
know deficits around this aspect of
syntax or or semantics so that's that's
kind of the obstacle that we have right
the obstacle we have is that we have
this very strange uh potentially human
specific seemingly very simple you know
process of just building hierarchical
structures but it's very difficult to
isolate um from all these other things
going on because as soon as you build a
sentence structure as soon as you build
a phrase or a sentence you are also
doing glow of other things you are also
using your attention you're also using
working memory you're also saying things
or reading things or engaging your eyes
or your ears so that's you know it
really is very difficult to isolate it
um so anyway that's that's that's the
problem that we have so I'll just skip
this part to the next section here so um
I'm just going to read through some of
this text and and maybe try and unpack
it a little bit more um but the past
decade has seen the emergence of low
frequency phase coherence as a feasible
index of hierarchical syntactic
structure will so what that means is
that if you read these papers um there's
low frequency oscillations in the brain
that can be detected using Meg or scal
Peg and they basically show little
fluctuations little little Peaks um uh
aligned with certain moments and periods
of or Windows of structure building I'm
just thinking of more metaphors little
little islands of structure that come
along when you pass a sentence in real
time whenever that moment of structure
building occures you seem to get this
low frequency peak in activity in the
brain um it tends to be around you know
classical language cortex like left left
inferior frontal cortex or temporal
cortex but the the actual spatial
temporal isolation is still a little bit
ify we still don't really know quite
frankly um so so that's the kind of you
know background for that aspect of
language at the same time though recent
work has also examined local cortical
processing using interc cranial
recordings so this is these are
recordings inside the brain and and what
they do is they often Focus instead on
high frequency power they can detect low
frequency power absolutely but most of
the analyses and novel findings within
the interrenal space have prioritized
looking into high frequency research and
for the simple reason that that's do in
real way that you can get hope you
recordings um so this works exposes
signatures of syntax um in in other kind
of areas outside of low frequency
Dynamics so there's a big question here
how these two distinct recording scales
low frequency you know Dynamics and high
frequency Dynamics could be combined in
a coherent model of natural language
syntax and quot
computation but has been addressed yet
so that's kind of one of the arguments
that I try and build here um so yeah
neural oscillations are effectively like
I mentioned they reflect synchronized
fluctuations in neuronal excitability
and are typically grouped by frequency
mainly for convenience but you know not
always there are in fact some uh there
seems to be something else going on um
common rhythms are often termed Delta
Theta Alpha Beta and then gamma um and
uh broadly speaking high frequency
activity reflects local neuronal
processing whereas lower frequency
activity reflects uh Regional
synchronization so high FR activity you
get that local cortical computation in a
specific brain region this brain region
is doing something as opposed to low FR
activity which is often more widespread
and it's all it's more to do with the
coordination of regional synchronization
so the low frequencies say okay it's
time for you guys to all come online at
this particular time to uh you
know engage your Spike activity in this
particular uh time period but over a
larger portion of tissue typically it's
over much much much larger areas of the
brain
um and then there's a bunch of other
kind of computational differences
seemingly as well between these lower
bands so for example Alpha is very often
implicated in cortical disinhibition it
kind of helps to shield and protect um
ongoing representations from you know
Decay and transformation and then Theta
oscillations often implicated in
hippocampus have been involved in
learning in memory there's a big
literature on that don't need to go into
the details but essentially there's a
whole you know panoply of low frequency
rhythms and they seem to be sensitive to
different cogni processes or at least
know recruited or they seem to index a
bunch of lower order processes
potentially okay um so one way to kind
of introduce this is through a model
that I proposed in my book in 2020 um in
this model again using invoking low
frequency power the combinatorial power
of language is indexed via various
cilory interactions like forms of cross
frequency coupling which is U basically
when the the phase of a lower frequency
Rhythm kind of coordinates and dictates
the firing of a high frequency Rhythm so
you kind of get a potential facilitation
of what's called multiplexing or kind of
packaging representations in one order
and then sending them Downstream and
kind of re re re accessing them from in
a different part of the brain um so in
this book of mine um there's a bunch of
kind of literature that's reviewed to
motivate the idea that Delta Theta phase
amp2 coupling constructs multiple sets
of syntactic and semantic features so
you get this initial low frequency phase
interaction between Delta and and Theta
and this occurs when the phase of Delta
is synchronized with the amplitude of
theta and Delta represents superordinate
syntactic categories whereas Theta
represents feature bundles generated via
electrical access what does that mean it
means that these Theta oscillations um
there something called the gamma
coupling famous um in memory research
and navigation uh theet gamma coupling
and in fact there's some really nice
work published yesterday I think by oans
and looking at how ATT tension might be
also implemented through Alpha Gamma
coupling but the basic idea is that you
have individual sets of features that
are you know basic mental
representations like things responsible
for you know animacy plurality uh basic
conceptual categories they seem to be
triggered by high fance activity and
then they're coordinated and packaged
into a single kind of Chunk by Theta so
you have a single low frequency Theta
wave and within that single wave you get
a bunch of individual you know five six
seven or eight how however many you can
kind of squeeze and fit in uh and
there's kind of tradeoff between
Fidelity and uh the kind of number of um
gamma oscillations you can package
inside a Peter cycle um but so that
packaging of theeta with gamma helps you
to kind of coordinate and unify uh an
individual representation in the you
know attention and visual spaces that's
been referred to as uh you know
coordinated visual attention when you
kind of your visual SE your visual uh uh
system is kind of attuning to particular
properties in the environment um in the
language space I'm kind of invok can get
to unify different individual features
that compose into alal item so alal item
is just a fancy word for for a word so
something like you know W talk yeah you
bed I'm just thinking of random words
all of these random words are obviously
composed of individual features
conceptual features right so a bed is
inanimate it's h you know has a
particular geometry it has a particular
function a purpose a design and so on
and all these different conceptual
features compose into what we mean by a
bed whenever you think of a bed or a
chair or a mirror um or you know Whole
Foods it could be anything it's simple
anything from simple to complex you have
a a constellation of conceptual features
that are being composed somehow and and
the idea here is that these low
frequency Theta oscillations are there
to coordinate the firings of those
individual features which is why you get
a lot of lexicality effects being found
in for example the theer range and then
what you do is in this model you get
those Theta bundles of flexible features
and you embed them further
so you Nest them again and what you do
when you Nest them again within a Delta
rhythm is that the Delta Rhythm then
takes over from the individual exal
items and it composes a syntactic
identity so a structure a structural
identity so for example it's been you
know well studied in linguistics that
when you uh put two items together two
words together you get a kind of
symmetry breaking operation where one of
the items kind of determines the
category of the phrase so for example um
if you say a red
boat um a red boat is a boat that is red
um a red boat is not a a red likee
quality that has you know boatlike
features for example um so there's a
kind of immediate asymmetry and you get
that all over the place if you say John
ran John ran does not mean that there's
a special kind of John who is exhibiting
a running feature it means that there's
an event of running and John was its
agent right so there's always an
immediate kind of asymmetry in language
and that's you people like the H others
have kind of speculated that one of the
interesting things about language is
that unlike music and Mathematics that
kind of allow symmetry in their
structures um language doesn't really
like symmetry as soon as you get
symmetry in language the language system
tries to break it somehow um because
there has to be some kind of uh
categorizer for you to identify What's
called the label or the category of of
the phrase for you to get a a single
unified syntactic representation so in
other words whenever you get two words
being combined together one of them
always wins and one of them is the loser
um and that's how you build syntactic
structures you get a kind of uh
categorization process so just to kind
of recap you have Delta beta and gamma
the Delta assigns or it somehow derives
or it facilitates the syntactic
inference of what the category is and
the reason who knows right I'll try and
explain some potential reasons here um
ultimately it's unknown but we do know
that in the empirical domain we get a
lot of these syntax signatures being
found in the Delta range so Delta seems
to care about chunking on some level
maybe not syntactic specific chunk
chunking but I think it's possible um
for reasons cited in the paper so Delta
and then and train then packages within
one of its waves multiple Theta rhythms
uh and the reason why is because the
same mechanism that you invoke when you
get Theta chemic bling so it's a series
of nesting you know nesting and and
nesting and nesting and you know the
whole Rose architecture uh in this paper
is basically trying to construct uh what
some people might think of as rather
crude but I think rather empirically
motivating in fact um isomorphic
relationship between structure and
neural kind of signal complexity right
uh it's it's common for people to think
well you know the brain is very
complicated language is very complicated
it surely can't be the case that a
particular level of linguistic structure
Maps directly onto a particular
resolution of for example illary phase
coding um I think there's good empirical
evidence to actually assume that um and
not everything uh takes place at the
lower course grain level at the spike
level for example or even inally I think
it's a it's unlikely that all these
complex processes from making inferences
about you know whether or not red or
boat wins and becomes the categorizer of
the adjective phrase is all taking place
at the intra or intracellular level um
at the kind of global you know the kind
of stuff that you can detect using uh
single unit recordings for example and I
think something more Global and uh you
know interactive is happening and that's
why you kind of need to invoke
some kind of phase code because the
phase code you only get that once you
transition to more Global
synchronization metrics of of the kind
found with low frequency Dynamics that's
the whole point of low frequency
synchronization so I think that's kind
of the kind of basic natural progression
that you find here at least in the way
that I motivated it in using the the
literature that I review in the book and
kind of is recapitulated here to a
certain
extent okay so then um we return to
something called phase resetting so
phase resetting um alongside concurrent
um encoding and storage of the products
of this these generated objects um
permits a facility for recursive sell
self cor and so that's kind of where you
get the recursive mechanism of language
you you're consistently renesting
objects into this more complex Delta
Rhythm um you know chunking out more and
more and more low frequency um uh
complexes essentially and just on the
side we also know that um from empirical
work by people in my lab and in the as
well that um you get a bunch of
different Dynamics alongside this so for
example we know that beta rhythms and
other types of um gamma rhythms are
involved in all sorts of different types
of um processes like um conceptual
storage and maintenance of a particular
structure in memory um so there's a very
kind of complex interplay here between
different rhythms and it's not intuitive
it's not easy to to grasp on F you know
I realize I'm not potentially not doing
the best job of explaining it because
there's a lot of things that unpack as
soon as you move to another kind of
concept you have to unpack it to a
certain extent but the basic idea is
that there's a number of interacting uh
low frequency rhythms that then dictate
the firing rate and coordination of
these faster rhythms and the faster
rhythms kind of are responsible for the
more um the kind of smaller more Atomic
features like individual electrical
items and the slower rhythms are
responsible for the more complex larger
structures like syntactic identities and
syntactic workspaces and things that you
construct so the kind of output I guess
the output of the syntactic generative
engine is found at the lower frequency
end whereas the input the kind of stuff
that you need to provide to the system
to um get any syntactic structure
building done in the first place like
for example lexical features you need at
least to access some features before you
can combine them in order to combine
something you need to have something to
combine those individual properties are
hosted by The High Frequency
oscillations essentially okay um and
then finally um traveling oscillations
are also going to be relevant here so
these are essentially these low
frequencies that I mentioned except they
exhibit a particular directionality they
migrate in Phase coherence across the
brain uh and what that means is they
coordinate the spiking of uh neural
clusters across the brain across fixed
points so they kind of move from one
part of the brain into another part and
as they do so as they uh the phase of
the low frequency is uh shifted across a
particular path they then um trigger
particular um spiking profiles of these
uh neurons that they that they that that
they travel across so it's a
coordination process and it's also of
course given the nature of a migration
path that naturally leads to the
conclusion that um as is often commonly
known different parts of the brain are
is are innately sensitive to particular
representational features of the
environment particular conceptual
features things like faces you know
places um orthographic information um
emotions and things like that um there's
a very big difference for example
between you know inferior parial cortex
and anterior temp cortex in terms of
which conceptual features they seem to
be sensitive to so if you get that
traveling profile you got that low
frequency um um you know uh uh phase
code moving across a particular extended
path then that immediately gets you
essentially for free it gives you um for
free the uh mechanism of activating
distinct conceptual um representations
during that process um so I think you
know there's a a lot of other things to
say here but traveling waves have been
implicated in a number of kind of
behavior relevant and processes in
humans and also nonhumans um and they
seem to support brain connectivity and
function more
generally um so yeah that's kind of the
background for for the traveling wave
mechanism um and then finally one final
thing to say here um I mentioned the
Delta Theta and Gamma complex there's
also been some interesting work outside
of language looking at um Delta gamma
FAL comcs so that's kind of skipping out
the middleman and simply involving this
low frequency Delta complex um uh being
face coupled with the amplitude of high
frequency gamma oscillations and what
that seems to be involved in is featural
combinatorics in general so for example
it's been involved in fluid intelligence
so when you have to just uh perform a
particular task or solve a problem
immediately and call upon various
cognitive representations from different
core knowledge systems in your mind lots
of different you know aspects of
intelligence you have to kind of recruit
here and there you don't necessarily
have to in fact you don't at all
construct a hierarchical structure you
don't constru construct a hierarchical
recursive representation you just
combine things together into a set into
a conglomerate to help you solve a
particular puzzle so that's what fluid
intelligence is all about um you also
get that with um certain early stages in
phrase composition in scalp so people
like Andre Martin and Jonathan Brennan
have done some nice work showing this um
so what that tells you is that there's
you know in language and also non
language you can combine features for
all sorts of reasons um when you comb
and if you if if you need to do that
Delta gamma coupling seems to be
sufficient and it seems to be a very
efficient way of doing that now if you
want to con construct an unbounded array
of you know hierarchically structured
Expressions I as I mentioned earlier
that might not be sufficient and so the
empirical argument I'm making here is
that um Delta gamma coupling will not be
sufficient for the kind of Rich um
syntactic you know phenomena that are
often documented in you know standard
textbooks for example so anything beyond
a basic phrase unit I suppose anything
with longdistance relations or
dependencies and things like that or in
fact anything beyond a single phrasal
structure will probably need to be um
call upon on all these other mechanisms
that I mentioned earlier the more kind
of richly layered uh levels of low
frequency interactions so um so Delta
gamma is fine for you know featural
combinatorics but it doesn't seem to be
sufficient again that's an empirical
claim could be wrong about that but it
doesn't seem to be sufficient based on
the literature for the more kind of
complex structures of the kind that we
uh that we all know and love in the
Linguistics World um okay and then we
can also make some interesting claims
here that I've made with my colleague
Antonio bonitz braco in in in Seville in
Spain um all these aspects of Hilary
Dynamics obviously result from somewhere
they don't come from nowhere they result
from genetic guidance um and some recent
workers provided a list of candidate
genes for this particular guidance so we
have a particular phase code and neural
code for syntax but it's got to come
from somewhere unless you're you
know well I'm not going to name any
names but unless you're the kind of
person who's so in love with um you know
deep learning and um large language
large language models that you you think
that it's all just some kind of EP
phenomenal domain General learning
process but if you don't believe that
then there's got to be some some kind of
genetic structure for language and so
we've mapped a bunch of these potential
genes um using a bunch of different
techniques um to uh particular uh
particular functions um but that's a
very much an ongoing kind of far off
project it's just the very beginnings of
trying to map out the kind of genetics
of the neural code for language but at
least it's a coherent project right it's
a legitimate coherent project although
rather nent too to be fair okay um so um
just to background this discussion a
little bit more I realized we're already
quite far in so I'll just kind of skip
ahead a little bit um one of the most
important questions in the new neurolog
syntax is essentially you know what type
of neural activity uh low frequeny
activity High frequeny activity Spike
rate can track very long or very brief
phrases so my basic answer which I've
already essentially given to you is
associating roughly the respective
scales of recording and neural
organization with particular levels of
linguistic complexity so low low
frequency gets you structures high
frequency gets you operations and Spike
individual uh Spike trains give you uh
basic representations okay so this
section here is slightly less important
for art purposes so I'll just skip over
it but essentially my claim in this
section of the paper section three is
just to kind of um review uh existing
models of um language in the brain
neurobiology of syntax and particular
and just to show that they essentially
tick U many of these boxes but not
necessarily all of them so certain
models emphasize the r or the O but they
don't talk about the s or the E uh or in
fact in my own book I talk about the the
O and s but I don't really talk about r
e at all in fact um other work talk talk
about um potentially a combination of
all these features but don't provide a
particular mechanistic um relationship
between how they uh how these features
relate so for example you can talk about
the neurobiology of R and O and S and E
but even if you have that you still need
to have some way of causally relating
them which is the kind of final section
of this paper which is how you get so
for example you know I mentioned that
the representations the r unit is hosted
at the SP level and the E the E unit
encoding is represented in low frequency
traveling waves but how the hell do you
connect those two things right how do
you directly what mechanism do you
coordinate them so we know there's some
recent work showing that in fact
traveling waves can in fact directly um
uh uh coordinate Spike lfp coupling
that's that's a very promising work
there to kind of unify all these
features together but you got to have a
mechanism to do that so you got to have
a separate mechanism in between RN o o
and and SN it doesn't just come for fre
um okay so a lot of these previous
models are very promising from a
cartographic perspective they really do
help us understand which parts of the
brain are involved in different aspects
of syntax or semantic um but in terms of
um providing the how question right like
which neural mechanisms exactly are
involved that's typically lacking uh the
best candidate you have is definitely
the work of Stander ha he's done some
really nice work showing that um
signature syntax might be in places that
most most people have not really thought
about
um especially at the the lower lower
order level in individual Spike spiking
activity or cellular barcodes and so on
um that's very promising and it's
something that I invoke in this paper in
fact as well um okay so just to
introduce this a little bit further um
these four components of rows RSC enter
into every syntactic phenomenon
everything as soon as you get a
syntactic structure you need to have at
least all of these things um okay so in
terms of
representations I Define them just like
any old uh mental representation
essentially um they are an instruction
to provide a particular conceptual
feature um they are composed of features
determining constraints on operations as
well and that's a really important Point
by the way I do want to stress that um
it's well known in linguistics that um
you know words have things like
selectional restrictions so a verb will
often cooccur or will need to ur with a
certain other word
um you can't just put words in any order
that you like um so you know words are
kind of like uh you know magnets they're
kind of try and attached to certain
other words and often that's independent
of statistics by the way there's some
good work by Andre Martin and Sophie
slats on the relationship between
statistics of language and structure in
language and they're not the same thing
at all they often correlate and they
often Aid each other in various ways in
very intricate ways but they're not the
same thing at all and you can't simply
derive all possible structured in
language just from the frequency but you
know frequency properties of words and
the Bagram and trigram frequency right
um you need something else you need kind
of structural information um so the fact
this is kind of a maybe a SLE point but
the fact that um individual
representations do in fact have
selectional and agreement and movement
constraints already tells you that
there's got to be some kind of
relationship between or dependency
between the nature of how we neurally
represent these representations and how
they then transition into the oper ation
stage right the O stage there's got to
be an initial dependency um so some of
these features can be maybe a little bit
Baro um but you know linguists often
talk about things like demonstrative
noun plural and so on um these are of
course human defined you know the way
that our conceptual systems work we've
tried to Define these things using these
terms um are these cognitively plausable
or neurologically posable uh maybe not
but there's at least some kind of atomic
unit that's being involved here a unit
just call it X right so this feature X
and Y they are being composed into
particular uh configurations so maybe
these terms these English language terms
are just a convenience a kind of
placeholder for what these conceptual
features really are so to speak but I I
think that language is slightly
misleading for a reason that people like
chsky and David poble have talked about
and a lot of these things really just
come down to the kind of classic Marian
levels you know David Mar's three levels
of computation algorithm and
implementation um all of these things
are totally kosher and legitimate at the
computational level and so therefore
it's it's doesn't really we don't really
have to abandon them necessarily just
because um we can't find a you know what
some what looks like a noun feature in
the brain that's you know a lot of this
involves kind of category errors I think
so which is why I try and break it down
into more Atomic stages um so syntax
builds structure through um recursive
applications of merge like I said you
have this basic merge operation which I
haven't introduced yet I realized but
it's basically just a binary set
formation with some kind of
categorization so you form a set um you
just put two things together and then
you categorize it you give a category um
you know a n phrase or a B phrase or
something like that and there's much
more to be said there but that's
essentially the basic property of
language just uh building sets set
formation um
okay so this is the outline of the model
um at the r level as I mentioned you get
single unit encoding of conceptual
features and what call formal semantic
formal syntactic features and these are
basically features that I won't bother
going into but there are certain
features um like q andf and other things
that are uh other features that are
interpretable or uninterpretable things
that are uh features that only enter
into syntactic relationships and don't
have any other a role they don't have
any any other role in providing
instructions to phology or um anything
else um but so the the these features um
involve uh a what's called a cellular
barcode for distinct features that
compose into syntactic objects
coherently Bound by this High gam
activity o so the O stage is is the
later stage uh and it also involves
Vector codes this is invoking a lot of
uh work from John Hopkins University and
people like stand again the r level also
involves Vector codes for ensembles
neural ensembles cellular ensembles
hosting features common to objects
represented at o and which are
ultimately coordinated by the S level
the low frequency level
um at the O level high gamma activity so
this high high gamma activity is like I
said it's neural activity that is around
you know 60 to 150 200 HZ amplitude in
the brain uh these this High gamma sentr
motor
Transformations um so things like high
gam activity provides access to cotor
Transformations and they transform these
Central motor um representations like
you know Sight and Sound and and
orthography and so on things that you
read things that you are exposed to they
transform them into lexes objects um and
if you're interested in the particular
Regional involvement there's a list
there um and then they are they they are
therefore accessible as I mentioned
earlier they're accessible to Delta or
Theta phase locking so I mentioned the
the Theta gamma coupling where the phase
of theta dictates the amplitude and the
firing rate of the high frequency
oscillations so though you know you only
get that once you have high gamma
activity um
because that's the that's the
sufficiently uh you know kind of correct
resolution the optimal resolution it
seems which the brain likes to
coordinate uh longdistance relationships
um and provide you know transfer
information from one part of the brain
to to the other essentially um so this
level can implement the semantic
composition of language specific
Concepts that coordinate the firing of
our units so that this this higham level
has also been implicated in basic
semantic composition so in a paper of
mine the I've looked at the composition
of basic adjective n structures using
interanal recordings and high gam
activity seems to be sensitive to this
basic aspect of semantic composition not
necessarily syntactic composition uh but
certainly semantic composition it could
also be involved in syntactic
composition um but certainly semantic
composition um uh syntactic composition
again would necessarily involve the S
level your s for
structure okay and then of course the
high Gamera um activity itself also
activates these ensembles that I
mentioned at the r level that are
composed of distinct units hosting this
barcode or vector code for the finite
list of units that compose into the
feature bundles that you get when
whenever you access an individual WID
every given WID is literally just a
linear list of these features that you
kind of trigger whenever you access it
um and again you know all of this stuff
is only talking about the syntax
semantic side the the side of phology
and sound and gesture and orthography
and all the rest of it that's a separate
issue that's a totally separate issue um
I'm only talking about interpretation
comprehension you know planning thinking
that kind of thing I'm just talking
about internalization here okay turning
to the S level um as I mentioned this is
a low frequency neural program for
generating uh structural inferences over
the O level um so Delta Theta phase amp
coupling as I mentioned uh gives you
categorial inferences that allow you to
modulate the representations of these
feature bundles so the Delta can
coordinate the theeta gamma complex and
it has some say in the sequencing and
the triggering and the the kind of um
like I said yeah basically the
triggering of these features and how
they are accessed um basically the
readout what what's term the readout
right and then finally e the encoding
phase um this is what I mentioned
earlier with the traveling waves where
you get the local and Global workspaces
for bottom up lexical memory and top-
down hierarchical memory um traveling
waves Implement Delta Theta coupling for
hierarchical memory whereas the theeta
gamma coupling gives you the kind of
bottom up lexical memory it's kind of
linearized memory just for lexical
features whereas the hierarchical memory
the the memory about um hierarchical
relationships in a structure so so you
know abstract relations in a Tre
structure uh independent of any linear
order or independent of any Sentry motor
Transformations triggered by gam the
kind of there's separability between the
structural inferences made and the uh
lower level Cent motor operations that
you get and are accessed by by
gam and then as I mentioned earlier as
well uh Alpha power can be involved in
this in the shielding of this of this
process um an increase in Alpha power
towards the end of sentences is often
indicative of like some kind of uh you
know acral of semantic attention or
semantic working memory or something
like that
um so I think that's potentially related
to this issue too um and then finally
beta power also codes for syntactic
predictions there been some interesting
work um looking at how beta power seems
to be be sensitive to um successful or
um unsuccessful but basically triggered
or not triggered syntactic predict
predictions or at least anticipation of
building a syntactic phrase or you're
about to you know you've been exposed to
certain words and now you're about to
generate a structural inference or you
predicting a specific syntactic item
beta power seems to be involved in the
indexing of that sensitivity um but
notice something interesting here right
that's beta power the this whole no this
whole notion of prediction and
anticipation that is a separate process
from the core structure building
inferential process involved in that's
been You exhibited by Delta and Theta
and has already been empirically
documented by in Delta and theeta so
again again this is a kind of
neurobiological support for the
separation of kind of you know
predictive algorithms predictive
processing and uh you know more kind of
oldfashioned traditional uh structural
uh inferences that are made by the
brain so you know just to unpack that a
little bit more it would be a problem
for me it would be a problem for a lot
of people if all of these processes
anticipation prediction you know
cordination um attention um and also
syntactic structural inferences were all
indexed and all coordinated in this
delter and or fet rythm that would be a
problem because how the hell do you
separate them out right it's very
difficult to think about that um you
know if that were to be true then we
would probably have to abandon the
notion that we can construct a coherent
oscillatory phase code for language it
might be impossible you just have to
just give up on it and look elsewhere
but the fact that we can in fact find
the separability I think speaks to this
potential um which is why I wrote this
paper because I think you know I think
there's some good um some good potential
here
okay and then this figure down here um
if I can maybe just zoom in a little bit
potentially um this just depicts um
exactly what I mentioned uh in varable
form in visual form so the
representation level uh again these
individual features here correspond to
individual cells sensitive maybe not
selective but sensitive to each of these
features the question of selectivity
basis sensitivity that's purely
empirical um I I enjoy you know
philosophy and and and theorizing as
much as anybody else but these questions
are at this stage purely empirical it's
it's possible that there are certain
cells that are selective or you know
sensitive to all these features but at
least that's that's the framework
there's a particular so infrastructure
that facilitates these U
representational accessing essentially
um when it comes to operation again I
need to be careful with the term
operation because I maybe this is the
one that I haven't explained well enough
so I should maybe spend a minute just
explaining this um there's the brain you
know carries out phological operations
it carries out semantic operations it
carries out syntactic operations it
carries out all sorts of operations in
the context of rows I want I'm focusing
on how it carries out the co the the the
combination the initial set formation
process involved in in in merge so the
early stage of merge essentially the O
versus S kind of captures the
distinction between mge and labeling
essentially um the distinction between
set formation just building you know
putting two units together um and then
transferring it into a category so I
guess what I'm trying to say is the
categorization process will not be found
at the O level at the high gamma level
you might see some category sensitivity
in high gamma you might see um different
gamma um profiles for you know verb
phraser versus noun phrases and in fact
we've already found that people like
Andrea Maro has published papers on this
so we know that um there's a syntactic
or semantic sensitivity at the O Level
again the difference between verb phrase
and noun phrase is not just syntactic
it's also semantic right that's the
problem big issue here of trying to
separate syntax from semantics is that
whenever you modulate syntax you also
modulate semantics and whenever you
modulate lexos semantic content you also
therefore modify everything else syntax
and semantics so that's an issue and
there you know we're trying to well we
are in fact uh you know running some
designs at the moment to try and
experimentally tease those apart but for
the for this purposes
um the current for the current purposes
the term operation is referred to
unifying um different semantic different
lexal and semantic features together
essentially into a coherent unit into a
set and then once you've got that set
represented in gamma then you turn to
the structural level and the structural
level is more higher order more complex
more Global more interactive and
therefore more low frequency right
that's the kind of goal that's the kind
of framework here um and then finally
finally um the encoding level I
mentioned very briefly maybe a little
bit too briefly the two types of
memories that you get in language
there's been some really good work by
people like David AER uh Queen Mary and
um a bunch of other people uh who've
kind of explored the uh different types
of syntactic workspaces or linguistic
workspaces like when you comprehend a
sentence you don't just have a single um
well you might in fact have a single
workspace it's possible but it's also
possible that you read it out into
different separable workspaces that that
responsible sensitive to different types
of memory um representations so it's
often been implied by people like
William matchin I think very
legitimately that inferior frontal
cortex is really um involved in
syntactic working memory um specifically
we don't know exactly what features of
syntax but C certain typ certain types
of um syntactic information are held
there and maintained there in shortterm
memory um but so uh for Lex memory I'm
invoking the gam coupling and then as I
mentioned briefly for the hierarchical
memory I'm involved I'm evoking Delta
Theta coupling and then unifying the
both of them or connecting the two was
this other form of processing that I
mentioned earlier the Delta um gamma
coupling right so the Delta gamma
coupling as I mentioned is just involved
in uh basic uh domain General very
domain General uh combinatorics just
combining two different representations
from different parts of the mind um but
nevertheless you'll see the relationship
between you know Delta and gamma uh
between both of them now when it comes
to the the spao temporal dynamics of
this process the actual kind of um you
know how this is implemented in in the
brain in terms of which networks uh
which white matter Pathways and so on
that's a purely empirical question but
we do know enough from the Meg from the
scalp literature from the inter cranial
literature that these codes are
legitimate codes to be implemented
across some portions of of Cortex um I
have a bunch of speculations empirically
supported
uh also in terms of which parts of the
brain these particular encoding
workspaces are going to be found and
going to be documented um but that's at
least this is the general abstract
schema if you like this is the kind of
very general um schema and the reason
why I've emphasize that is because as I
mentioned earlier every other paper in
um neural Linguistics focusing on syntax
is almost entirely uh cartographic it's
almost entirely localizationist in terms
of let's figure out if it's you know is
it if is it PT you know is it ventral
temporal um they're the kind of
questions that are framed by most of
these models in the literature and
though essential that's not my concern
here right my concern here is yes
localization but let's try and focus on
which particular abstract neural code is
going to be generalizable enough across
different part parts of the brain and
also by the way small Point here um also
generalizable across cases of plasticity
um you know I'm involved in a neur
neuros case today we know the brain is
highly plastic when you reect certain
portions of tissue recruited or not in
language you get fairly rapid
organization over the over the over a
period of weeks and months sometimes
years um but that tells you immediately
and in fact there's some also really
fascinating work in can congenitally uh
blind people and or de blind I think too
um showing that uh portions of their um
uh yeah in the congen blind there's
portions of oxital Cortex that come
online and are sensitive to syntax so
because you know these people are not
using their acceptor cortex for vision
they don't need it uh they end up uh
recruiting it for other other purposes
to sometimes linguistic purposes so
that's why I think focus on a more
abstract code is more important maybe
not more important maybe that's maybe
that's unfair but I think it's
potentially just as important if not
more important than trying to figure out
the kind of cartographic landscape um
but for how language is implemented uh
also by the way another small point
which is maybe not not so small these
days um this is also very important if
we care about things like brain computer
interface devices so uh you know neurot
Technologies um so there's a bunch of uh
what's called BCI brain computer
interface devices that you implant in
patients brains uh to help them uh with
either their epilepsy or to help them uh
with speech processing you get quic
patients who who lose their speech um
and there's some other efforts recently
to try and help people with you know all
sorts of language deficits by using
neural implants um there's a you know a
factory not too far away from me north
in Austin and uh there's there's places
you know owned by Elon Musk as you know
uh who's who owns neuralink these guys
are trying to do something similar but
you know that's a speech when it comes
to using it uh designing a brain
computer interface for things like
syntax or semantics I think we're going
to need to pay attention to these
aspects these questions to do with the
neural code rather than just the region
because if you're going to have somebody
who has a syntactic deficit or a itic
deficit and you're going to try and help
them get their language faculty back
it's no good just knowing which part of
the brain is going to be recruited for
their language function with a BCI
device you need to coordinate particular
uh stimulation profiles and particular
ways to coordinate and Trigger and
suppress brain activity and so in order
to do that you got to have the right
parameter space and to figure out the
parameter space you therefore need to
have a question of neural code involved
almost definitely a phase code uh some
kind of high frequency or low frequency
B code so all of these questions that
I'm that I'm asking right now don't just
have kind of theoretical you know basic
science academic implications obviously
that's my interest that's that's my main
concern here but they will also
definitely have kind of you know
implications for patient treatment um in
the BCI Space Mo moving
forward
okay right then let's let's move on
let's skip past some of this um I've
it's getting on to uh almost an hour now
so I'll skip through um the next few
sections are just outlining
representation operation structure and
encoding so I'll just pick out some of
the most um important moments from here
um but again this section number five
just defines redefines again maybe
exhaustively um the what I mean by
representation some example features um
and in fact what um these gamma
oscillations and high frequency
oscillations might be indexing more
generally in terms of their cognitive
scope and their computational kind of
facility um this is just a little brief
definition of the kind of scales that
are relevant to the different levels so
we have single unit activity multi-unit
activity uh the envelope of Spike and
the lfp these are different aspects of
new organization and recording
resolution that will be relevant to the
different components of rows and that
kind of that kind of just outlines the
the scope of of of inquiry here um this
was something that I put in to satisfy
make it clear that you know I'm talking
about representation in this sense and
not that sense um basic units again I'm
just talking about what these basic
units
are um and then I'm turning here to
concerns about um how to distinguish it
from things like
operations um okay and then oh yeah so
this is an important paragraph I think
um so this recent work by Nelson FAL
discovered preferential activity for um
content words function words in the
anterior temporal Lo this is single unit
recordings again I should I should
stress sorry um so that already begins
to tell you that at the single unit
level at the C Level different parts of
the brain I mentioned ATL already in
this case ATL does seem to be sensitive
to lexical Type U again that could be
due to other reasons in this case they
looked at it independent of we length
and we position uh the big confound
areas where frequency but you know
there's there's some other kind of
indication here that potentially
something to do with lax of ality uh is
driving this difference this sensitivity
um
okay um and then more generally um what
water term concept cells that
preferentially activate for stimuli that
occupy a certain position in some
category axis uh seem to support a
declarative seem to support declar
information what does that mean it just
means that there's a really some really
nice work by Bal um uh showing that
there's a kind of feature space um in uh
primate and also human um bral tempor
cortex that is sensitive to a a kind of
axis of animacy so whether or not an an
object is animate or inanimate um like a
chicken versus a laptop there's some
things that are kind of in between and
vague and then whether or not a surface
is spiky or stubby so kind of you know
uh like this or spiky so kind of kind of
a Kiki Boer kind of situation for for
linguists so that's kind of a nice
conceptual um geometry that you have
going on and there's different cells
concept cells that preferentially
activate for stimuli that occupy a space
within that axis um so that tells you
very nicely that at the unit level we
have a potential neural code for this
very you know generic but also
all-encompassing um object space um this
is Doris s laab the barel paper um so
you know the kind of um promise the
promise that this gives us for
linguistic features I think is quite
interesting because linguist have spent
a long time uh you know reminding us
that um the uh feature space in uh
linguistic semantics can also occupy
something like anime in anime um and
then some other a bunch of other
abstract concrete kind of feature spaces
too um so I think it's very reasonable
to to expect and to predict uh at the
unit level a similar kind of you know
conceptual geometry uh taking place in a
different part of the brain uh
potentially posterior temporal cortex
potentially inferior frontal cortex you
know who knows we don't know until we
until we explore but um I think that's
that kind of you know reinforces the uh
the uh the definition of the um of the r
level um that I'm defining here
okay uh right
then okay so this this next section here
mapping from artto this gets the the
very tricky issue that I mentioned at
the beginning so at the beginning of the
paper I you know Lampoon and criticize
all the the people for not doing this so
hopefully I do it you know a decent job
otherwise I will embarrass myself a
little bit um but the kind of motivation
here is that we don't just need a
definition of what R and O looks like in
the brain we need a way to relate R to O
we need a way to feed the information at
the r level the unit level all the way
up to the O level um so I mentioned just
a quick a quick reminder R is a single
unit you know Spike train activity um
the O level is high gam activity right
so they're kind of slightly more um uh
easy to detect using inter standard
inter cranial measures for example okay
so how can we relate these these ideas
the o to the
R so in this section um I kind of um
propos that the relations between
multi-unit activity and population
signals hold the answer okay uh so I
might just have to focus on this for a
little bit oh this is only a short
section very short section that's that's
good okay this will be quick then so um
local field potentials reflect the uh
the common synaptic synaptic activity of
a population of neighboring neurons um
and spikes are shorttime high frequency
content signals reflecting individual
cellular activity right so individual
cells neural synchronization can be
evinced one of my favorite words there
they can be evinced by temporally
relating spiking activity to the
background oscillations of lfps um and
this relationship has been documented
across multiple brain regions and
cognitive functions so this Spike phase
coupling has functional consequences and
there's some examples to if you want to
if you want to consult okay so that's
the coupling between um the lfp and the
actual Spike the individual Spike so
that's kind of an analogous right if you
think about it that's analogous to what
I mentioned earlier in the low frequency
space right I mentioned the Delta Theta
coupling and the uh you know the Delta
gamma coupling Etc this lfp phase
coupling is essentially the same thing
just at a small scale right so it's kind
of nesting all the way down um so lfps
are a highly effective means of exposing
what what state a given cortical region
is in since they capture General
Dynamics not specific to any individual
cell and this is really a really cool
Point actually about lfps they actually
host uh you know uh types of information
that are not detected at the spike level
so that's a very kind of an important
point there um and also of course you
know there are cells I don't Spike to
right um so in the same way that there's
likely much information available at the
lfp level that's not represented at the
unit level um like Dynamics and amas
properties exist that can only be
detected at the level of su activity
over a mil of neurons so too is expected
to be the case that there are aspects of
qual computation that are only
represented at the interactional global
stale scale even at the state scale like
you know hidden marov um scale kind of
um Auto Progressive hidden marov models
and so on you can kind of generate these
more abstract State spaces across
networks of brains uh networks of brons
sorry um and I think that will also be
relevant at some point too in the future
but maybe I'll get to that at some point
later um and and this and that
information is not represented at the
lfp or Spike level so that that basic
finding empirical finding is another
core motivation for the rose model right
the fact that you do find this um
dissociable level of um information
representation across these scales
already tells you it already tells you
that there's very likely to be this
scale of computational complexity
um at the linguistic and nonlinguistic
level
too okay and like I said it's a basic
pres presupposition of rows but it's
also a presupposition of other major
Frameworks in ctive Neuroscience right
not not just me I'm not the one to kind
of you know propose this um so an
example I candidate here is working
memory which seems to involve
discontinuous bouts of spiking activity
as opposed to steady state neural
Dynamics right so often it was initially
believed that working memory in order to
maintain something in working memory
there's got to be some kind of direct
intuitively direct neural correlate
which looks like it's maintaining or
staying at a stable level or you know
amplitude uh uh steady state or increase
over time Etc turns out not to be the
case um okay so relating R to O is far
from trivial yes that is absolutely
correct um consider how communication
through coherence has typically been
assumed to reflect pH synchronization
between oscillators recent workers
offered an alternative mechanism through
which coherence is the consequence of
Comm communication and emerges because
spiking activity in ascending area
causes post synaptic Potentials in the
same but Al also other areas that makes
things more complicated um so these
authors identified um afer and synaptic
inputs rather than spiking entrainment
as the principal determinant of
coherence opening up new directions for
framing the relation between units and
coherence so lfp coherence appears to be
determined by two factors coherence due
to the direct contribution of afference
synaptic inputs and coherence between
the sender lfp and the sum population
spiking connectivity in the receiver so
therefore coherence therefore depends on
connectivity strength and oscillation
power and does not need purely
oscillatory coupling or Spike phase
locking in a receiver and then fav
complexities arise here I mentioned some
examples um from our neighboring field
too but I'll kind of skip over that it's
an interesting topic um but still you
know successfully relating the two
fundamental signals um in the section
Spike and lb can provide is with a
comprehensive explanation regarding the
neurobiological cognition um and since
many signals picked up by the lfp will
also very likely be able to be found at
the unit level care must be taken to map
out assembly level effects from single
unit responses and that's kind of an
empirical caution um so this kind of
section is very I think it's very honest
I think it's very upfront about the
limitations and potential um you know
counterveiling Trends in the literature
that provide some obstacles to this
grounding but nevertheless I think um
even if these things you know are true
there's still the possib defer multiple
types of phase codes multiple types of
neural codes within the same space um
being involved in different types of
cognitive operations or across different
code knowledge systems um and of course
you know given that we know that um
human syntax is in fact a potentially
species defining property I think it's
you know care must be taken to really
separate out the separate out from these
constellation of domain General neural
mechanisms which might be relevant but
might also not be relevant right it's
again that that's you have to kind of
weigh up the the likelihood of a domain
General versus non-domain General
process being relevant for your concern
and again you don't know until you know
you don't know until you um do the
Empirical research um but I think you
know the purpose of this subsection is
to kind of open up the space of you know
possible alternative
mechanisms okay I'm going to skip over
this section this is just discusses gain
field mechanisms I've written a few
papers about this uh it's a very
interesting topic uh just kind of
grounding the kind of lower level
accounts of why you know what it is what
it is we know already about
um uh what the computational properties
of uh individual cells might in fact be
and that might sound a bit abstract but
there's some really good work by uh W
tum of fit and Randy gallol and uh a
bunch of people that I cite here um just
exploring the potential computational
kind of uh you know uh kind of classical
touring level architecture you know
chumsky hierarchy kind of computational
um you know facility that these
individual Souls might have uh in terms
of the
uh operational
power okay and then this this subsection
here just introduces um a kind of a more
classical distinction between sharing
tonian and hot fian views that's
basically just um a distinction that
focuses on um the transformation of
signals by nodes in a point BYO
architecture viewing cognition as the
result of patterns of no to node
connections uh as opposed to viewing
representational spaces um through which
computation is considered to be the
transform between spaces um so it's kind
of a more different ways of viewing um
populations and units the relationship
between units and their population
Dynamics um and I kind of speculate
that's you know um evolutionary older
brain areas might be explained better be
sharing tonian accounts whereas more
recently evolved structures in hint
language right uh might not be so that's
a potential uh Avenue that could also
direct a way of uh exploring the kind of
empirical space be on this and then when
it comes to the operation space I've
already mentioned much of this stuff I'm
invoking high gamma
activity um I am talking about the uh
different oh yeah well there's different
dimensions to gam right gamma is a not
just a unified uh you know construct
either neurochemically or genetically in
fact it's a very complex structure
indeed across species across brain
regions you get physiological gamma
responses in subcortical structures you
get kind of higher order cognitive um
responses in in cortex gamma itself is
just you know lit is a range um but it's
a very a complex manifold um so I kind
of this section kind of takes care to to
break down what I mean by gamma um you a
lot of papers in the Neurology of
language just kind of invoke you know
gamma oscillations um or particular
arbitrarily cut off uh you know range uh
band range this section tries to take a
little bit of care to just unpack the
different types of gamma different types
of um aspects of gamma in terms of their
sensitivity to different aspects of um
representational complexity um so lower
versus high gamma you know Broadband
narrow narrow band gamma Etc um if
you're interested in that that's this is
a good section for you to consult
um
okay so turning to scripture this again
kind of reviews some of the things I
mentioned earlier to do with the fact
that you know every linguistic structure
is sensitive uh to some aspect of
lexical and sematic information like
cohere into some uh some kind of phrasal
or sentence structure uh there's a
phrase by alaran there's no escape from
syntax um that is absolutely true you
know everywhere you look in language
every time every kind of phenomenon
semantic pragmatic even phological
there's often a very uh direct impact of
syntactic information in terms of the
coordination and the instructions and
the influence it has on the on these
other levels um syntactic structure
really is the most kind of fundamental
level of of language that has uh
influences a bunch of different domains
um I've already introduced merge so I'll
just kind of skip over this this is just
a kind of more SE theoretic classical
definition of what we mean by featural
combination of the kind involved in
language and of the kind involved in the
kind of work that I mentioned earlier um
and of the kind involved in the uh the
high frequency gamma and Theta dynamics
that I mentioned earlier too so Mage is
basically the most fundamental operation
in language it's it's the basic property
of language as chumsky calls it um okay
uh again from a more philosophical
perspective I always found it
interesting that even though this is a
very rudimentary set formation operation
if you think about the cognitive
consequences as people like pet hag have
in a very nice paper um the
computational system of language seems
to be related to neural signals
integrating perception and action and
providing humans with uh novel modes of
planning and interpretation where by
electrical units and unification
processes like merge provide an
imaginary space that transcends the
influence of direct perception action
Cycles that's a really key point there
because of course we know that um one of
the um real benefits of language and
potentially why it was evolutionarily
selected for uh is because it allows us
to plan interpret think you know
consider personal responsibilities uh
you know consider our own future our
past and so on um construct a notion of
um um you know one's past and and where
you've been conr Nar so to speak right
so we know that other other animals have
memories but maybe none of them have a
past right maybe maybe only humans have
a have a past it's kind of a unique kind
of concept um that involves some kind of
a different epistemological transition
and a linguistic translation too right
it's a it's a fundamentally linguistic
notion same with the self right the
concept of self you know who I am and
who you are I are you and so on uh the
the the existence of the the pronoun
system language for example all of these
things are extremely cognitively rich
and semantically very important Concepts
they're not just there to facilitate
communication they're not just there to
facilitate information transmission they
really are part of the mental uh
architecture that we have as as human
beings so I think it's an important
point that H go makes there the fact
that this really is the center of the
kind of cognitive
neurosciences
okay um excuse me this section just
introduces um uh syntactic features what
we mean by particular syntactic feature
I mentioned electrical features quite a
lot um but this section kind of just
briefly touches on syntax specific
features um and it also reviews some
recent work looking at um the role of
endogenous oscillations in neural
computation I mentioned some of the
stuff earlier to do with low frequency
sensitivity and entrainment to
particular moments of syntactic
structure building this section here
just kind of unpacks some of that more
uh exhaustively and give some more
recent um references
there um so this section kind of just
reviews that
literature um skipping through this part
here um and again just kind of to
recapitulate what I mentioned earlier um
the role of low frequencies in indexing
super lexical structural inferences is
very well empirically supported so the
previous two pages that I just scroll
past they really kind of propos um
summarize a lot of literature suggesting
that lower frequencies indexing superal
lexical so stuff above the individual
Word level it really is pretty
undeniable at this stage I think um
okay and then we turn to the more issues
of timing so you know uh what is the
precise timing of syntactic um
information processing this paragraph
here just kind of breaks down some of
the particular periods of sensitivity
that have been already documented and
how it is compatible and maps on to the
predicted time Cod dictated by The High
Frequency rhythms right so it's no good
me just saying oh Delta is involved in
syntax and you know gamma in you know
semantics or whatever you really need to
have a motivated time course in real
time like a real- Time passing
constraint on how these um high
frequency oscillations can embed
themselves and be entrained uh and phase
locked to these um these these higher
pre these lower frequency rhythms and so
I kind of just break down the time
course of activity here um and it's all
kosher it's all you know empirically
motivated it's all kind of aligned with
what we know about both about Delta and
about the intermediary frequencies
too okay and then this section turns to
again the mapping process that I
mentioned um the mapping from the o to S
structure so this kind of invokes again
a separable mechanism um I'll just
scroll look to the top here just a
another quick
refresher so we had um phase amp cou as
I mentioned right so this is Spike phase
coupling mapping R to O mapping o to S
is Phase amplitude coupling so that's
the kind of classical process that I
mentioned earlier to do with Theta gamma
and Delta um gamma coupling because I
get you directly to the higher order
structural
inference
okay
so that is a this section is just a
short review of the phase amp cing
Dynamics in this particular process and
also talks a little bit about some other
kind of extracranial um excuse me
recording measurements that have kind of
uh unveiled this in other kinds of
domains uh this section here
dissociating structure from meaning this
is very much for the linguists this is
kind of trying to figure out um how we
can carefully account for signals that
are specific to the semantics of a
phrase versus signals that are maybe
spec maybe not specific but certainly
sensitive to the syntax of a phrase
that's a very tricky issue you have to
kind of basically uh design an
experiment or stimuli that is getting
participants to you know pay attention
to structural inferences and syntactic
information and syntactic acceptability
and not pay too much attention to other
kind of features but also the stimuli
itself have to be carefully weighted
across um you know words that uh
preferentially engage uh syntactic
information over and above conceptual
information or conceptual semantic
information versus words that very much
do trigger um heavy semantic content so
that involves a lot of you know careful
kind of empirical consideration um our
lab is currently carrying out you know
some research into that into that space
um as are some other labs too um but
it's basically a an appeal for focusing
more laser like on these you know ways
to dissociate syntactic from syntactic
syntactic from semantic processing um
using empirical uh you know novel kind
of experimental for paradigms because a
lot of the paradigms that are used at
the moment have a big problem which is
they don't really carefully separate out
moments of syntax from moments of
semantics so it's very difficult to kind
of you know realistically um and you
know kind of confidently make it clear
that a given brain signal or a given
response is really being driven by
either syntax or
semantics
okay um in terms of uh skip over this no
I didn't
okay and then this um outlines the the
mapping from the S to e levels and it
talks a little bit more about some of
Stander um and uh other people's work
into Vector codes for uh population
Dynamics um to do with what level of um
representation we might find individual
syntactic features at um and again I I
transition slowly here to talking about
traveling waves how the kind of the more
kind of static code that I've presented
so far in terms of just you know a Delta
a Theta a gamma how that static code
might be transfigured into something
more you know cognitively and
neurochemically plausible in terms of
the what we know about the
transformation of U information across
white mat tracts and across and how
different um portions of Cortex cortical
cortical cortico cortical information is
kind of transferred in real time across
different portions of the cortical
mantle it's not just like
stationary um okay so I guess what I'm
kind of calling for here and as I call
for in the next section is a more kind
of spatial temporally Dynamic uh model
or code for language
essentially excuse me so all of this
section essentially needs it kind of
calls upon the notion that you need to
map on a um an important you know
important findings from the psych
linguistic domain in terms of the timing
of language the kind of um you know uh
when we know that language is coming
involved which periods of activity are
going to be important and the actual
neural architecture that's kind of a
very tricky question how you map on
those those so for example you know if a
psych linguist says okay we know that
when people using eye tracking or using
scalp Erp responses we know that the
period of 300 to 400 milliseconds is
when most people kind of detect semantic
violation
effects we really then have to say okay
if that's the case does that time period
at the behavioral level map on to
moments of uh you know uh neural
activity also at that level or maybe
potentially the neural response comes on
a little bit earlier before it's
detected the scalp level or maybe at the
single unit level it's even earlier or
vice versa or maybe there's a kind of
top down uh effect whereby um some kind
of intermediary misos scale um you know
neural signal can be detected first
before the spiking information is it it
you know there's different hypotheses
that arise here um in terms of their
directionality and cause relation
between the r to e e levels um in this
in the Rose paper I make it you know
very clear what my empirical predictions
are but you know other alternative ways
to to modify the rose model could be in
terms of the directionality from
different levels right so for different
linguistic Scriptures it could be the
case that some of the more misos scale
levels in fact influence the
coordination of spiking rather than the
spiking information being read out at
kind of high order levels uh which then
which then facilitate the inferences
being made um the fun ality is very
clear in the paper but it's kind of open
it's very much open for empirical uh you
know resolution essentially okay so in
this figure figure two uh figure one is
the basic kind of you know components of
the model figure two is the basic
mechanisms of the model so this just
goes into some more technical details
that I won't go into uh to do with the
actual nature of Spike gy coupling what
the kind of mathematical foundations of
it are um and how you can you know map
that on uh to uh a kind of classic IAL
kind of low frequency response um and
how how these different signals could be
coordinated um in real
time
okay and then turning to the encoding
section as I mentioned earlier um you
know we we know that the human mind
needs different workspaces for different
aspects of cognition um so the big
question is does language share a
workspace with other kind of you know
nonlinguistic uh uh processes is there a
specialized uh unique workspace for
linguistic information it's possible um
I think it's likely in fact which is why
I have it in my paper um so in fact we
know that um there are some non-human
primates that can uh execute very
primitive um uh combination and
processes like potentially even more
flal composition just combining two uh
calls you know like Prime vocal calls
together into a basic primitive um unit
um can they then do it again and again
and again can they do they have the
workspace that allow a facilitation of
storing this one unit and then creating
a new structure and then you know
assigning that whole complex an identity
that is independent from its discrete
Parts which is what mge is all about in
language H they don't seem to be able to
do that so that tells you I think quite
reliably that we do need some kind of
notion of um human specific syntactic
workspace which is what the whole
encoding level is meant to be in row
and okay so so this section kind of just
plays out a little toy example um of
what how to derive a particular
structure and what the whole um uh
process would look like going from R to
O uh to e so I think this is important
for me to kind of outline since the part
of the paper where I kind of really do
give a concrete example so let's
consider the sentence uh old men walk
slowly uh during the compion of the
first two words the uh Delta gamma
combinatorial code coordinates the
feature bundling of the atomic data
structures hosted by alen men so Olden
men have various features um at a
minimum this involves posterior Superior
tempal sulcus low frequency activity
coupled with neighboring uh posterior
Temple cortex but also cross cortical
sites responsible for the specific
feature types in question so I've
already mentioned places like ATL and
ifg and then I also mentioned uh feta
gamma coupling uh this maintains in
shortterm memory I mentioned the
electrical memory Booker before the
gamma coupling maintains in short-term
memory the relevant units via High
activity um obv oh in a linear sequence
so this is worked by David po too the
Theta gamma coupling is a linear feature
clocking mechanism that tells you these
are the set of features features 1 to
five 1 to 7 and you're going to access
them and triggle them and read them out
in a given sequence so that's the kind
of linear lexical memory stuff it
doesn't give you the hierarchical uh
syntactic relational component that is
independent of order that comes
later okay um at the transition between
men and walk so word two and word three
the superordinate Delta Theta code
maintains the categorial identity of the
object so you know old men is obviously
um men that are old right as I mentioned
it's not an Old Quality that happens to
be men um so that's a noun phrase when
you get to Old Men walk you relabel the
object and it's no longer a noun phrase
right you have to recategorize the
syntax um it's not a verb phrase It's
old men doing something it's an event
structure so things like event
structures and uh you know
quantificational structures and all the
rest of it they involve very specific
unique semantics and that are informed
and provided by and configured by the
syntactic category so that's why I
mentioned that you know there's no
escape from syntax right the syntactic
category feeds the semantic information
okay so when you get to the the Theo
walk the superordinate uh Delta Theta
code maintains the categorial identity
of the object in this case the
negotiation between a multi-unit noun
phrase and a more complex verb phrase is
hosting old men so during the same
period the lexical memory code again if
you remember the lexical memory code is
the theet gamma the electrical memory
code increases its number of fet and
nested chunks due to the occurrence of
walk right so old men walk
is in terms of the theam code all the
theam code sees is another word when
when you get to war all the fic code
sees is a third word that's it it just
sees okay another word's coming another
word another word and it just simply
chunks those features together uh using
the feature clocking mechanism that I
mentioned um but that's not what the
what the Delta complex sees right that
se something else so the superordinate
Delta Theta code maintains the identity
um and in this negotiation between uh
and in this case the negotiation between
a multiunit phrase and a more complex
phas right during the same period the
initial lexical memory code increases
number of p and Trunks due to the G work
the same transition occurs from walk and
slowly with the exception that while the
electrical memory code still increases
in Clic strength um that's the
measurement of pack relations between
the the gamma right High pack relations
uh the hierarchical memory code would
decrease closer to but not identical its
pre- Baseline due to the um adjunction
relation not demanding a revision of the
hierarchical memory representation so
what the hell does that mean um so when
you get to Old Men walk you change the
uh syntactic um category it's a verb
phrase so that that involves a activity
at the Delta Theta level when you got
old men walk slowly the word slowly does
not change the syntax the word it's
still a verb phrase so old men walk
slowly is a verb phrase old men walk is
also a verb phrase so slowly changes the
gxo semantic information so you keep
getting that Theta gamma hack increase
but you get either a steady state or a
decrease again I predict the decrease of
the um Delta Theta pack relationship
because all you're doing is maintaining
the same syntactic identity you don't
need to change the syntax same same
syntax again I talked about syntax
feeding semantics if you think about it
for a second um old men walks slowly is
still uh involves old men it could be
old men walk quickly old men walk you
know um
lethargically um whatever uh it's still
the same thing so the fact that old men
work slowly doesn't change the fact that
it's still old men whereas with old men
walk that does change the fact about old
men so when we get to Old Men we have
certain facts we know about old men when
we get to Old Men walk that changes
things we know that it's old men walking
when we get to Old Men walk slowly it's
that's a modification structure it's
called an adjunct the adun structure or
you know adverb or prep prepositional
phrase anything like that simply it
doesn't it adjoins so that only involves
um basic set formation it doesn't
involve a re relabeling of the category
itself because the category is still the
same um so that and this gets into some
theoretical syntax ideas that are not
important here but the basic idea is
that you just get an an uh you know
enhancement of lexico semantic
information but the syntax is identical
so that's why you get this kind of wave
of old men walk and then slowly and this
is you know I mentioned some of the
Delta Peaks before
this kind of stimuli old men work slowly
is what has allowed researchers to
figure out that you get those low
frequency Peaks at the third word old
men walk slowly because that's that's
the period where you really change the
syntax H and it turns it into you know a
kind of sentence I guess a kind of full
sentential structure um with a
propositional identity uh you know truth
evaluable evaluability it can be true it
can be false uh you can you can afford
all sorts of different epistemic Jud
judgements to it um that's that's the
whole kind of um you know you kind of
get a a whole complex of instructions
being sent to conceptual systems at that
stage okay so the transfer of relevant
Leal information from Cate you know
categorization or labeling that I
mentioned would take place via
interactions between these two neural
codes right so separable codes um I
speculate here potentially the Theta
Theta um phase phas coupling or phase
locking of the uh Theta Gam workspace
and the uh Delta Theta workspace um
Theta driven Dynamics effectively
constitute the handoff of information
after electricity has been established
by lower level RN o processes
transitioning from encoding electrical
memory to to multiobject memory and
direct testing of these Dynamics
specifically with respect to syntactic
workspace instruction has currently not
been undertaken although much work has
been carried out demonstrating increased
theam coupling in human hippocampus
during Mo formation as well as enhanced
frontal Theta to posterior gamma
coupling alongside the recent discovery
of a rapid neocortical Thea Network
mechanism for flexible information and
coding and uh familiar operations from
left corner MIM list grammar can be
appropriately par slated onto these r o
and S levels that's a bunch of jargon uh
but the linguist will will appreciate
what I'm talking about there I hope um
but future work should still you know
treat this issue of precise passing
models with more care intact than I have
demonstrated here in this initial
architectural proposal so what I'm
trying to say there is that um you know
I mentioned Mars computational
implementational and uh uh algorithmic
level in the middle I've talked a lot
about computation and implementation
I've only spoken a little about about
the algorithm the thing connecting the
wet wear the kind of biological you know
uh stuff you can touch and see with the
kind of uh more abstract algorithm in
between the computation um and that's
the that's the domain of what's called
cych Linguistics so the field of
psyching istics has a bunch of different
passing architectures for how humans
pass sentences there's rival models uh
lot of them have different uh you know
predictions for how um human beings pass
different types of weird sentences in
real time um that's I have my own
favorite candidate I've I've mentioned
left corner minute passes um that's kind
of my own uh you know favorite account
for all sorts of empirical and
theoretical reasons um but it's an open
question and in fact later I kind of
discuss the possibility that different
parts of the brain might Implement
slightly different passing models um so
you know the posterior temporal cortex
might be a good place to find a minus
grammar but the uh you know inferior
Pari cortex or the inferior frontal
jarus might be an excellent place to
find a different kind of paring model
and I I cite a bunch of examples in the
paper somewhere in here I think um but
that's again an question but it's also
kind of a more I think it's a more
pluralistic way of kind of viewing
language in the brain you know it's not
just like you know minim passing
grammars explain everything and the
entire brain is you know a in
concordance with the predictions of
minimal grammas it might be a kind of
more uh a different kind of
constellation of of of pares that we
need um but still nevertheless with the
basic primitive uh you know
computational architecture being uh
infected by moments of merge and
labeling and kind of more traditional
basic assumptions from G grammar okay
uh this this moment just uh yeah this
period just turns a little bit more
towards traveling waves um and a little
bit more to do with FM research kind of
building the paper more to what we
already know from the extracranial
world um this section talks about uh
syntactic memory as being a phase
synchronization over successive Cycles
so this invokes a bunch of interesting
work and consults some models from um
the uh uh the world of uh the
neurobiology of oscillations more
generally in terms of phase Dynamics and
cross coupling and all the rest of it
just to kind of situate what the model
might look like in a more kind of
mathematically rigorous fature
space um the section on symbolic
computation uh turns a little bit more
to um what we already know about um uh
in fact I think I should I should review
this very quickly because this this this
again comes back to the issue of domain
story so um Rion directions in the
neurobiology of navigation and memory
are relevant to the conception of
e um so hipocampal cortical sequence
replay and encoding is not constrained
to Simply repeat past experience rather
this process is informed by an internal
model of the world generating
representations of inferred entities not
necessarily encountered physically again
this is one of the reasons why I I work
with people like Carl Kristen because I
think this whole notion of uh you know
building a gender model of one's
environment the interplay of action and
perception cycles and so on that's
really a
fundamental you know
negotiating uh a building block of of
what language gives us of what what the
role of language really is in the human
mind it's really about interplaying
these two different um uh divides of of
of the human brain uh so this active
generative capacity motivates the
authors to propose that Replay in the
brain instantiates a form of
compositional
computation so a given replay sequence
constitutes a set of entities strung
together into a compound whereby each
entity is bound to a representation of
its compound role determining its
function as part of the whole this
establishes a clear separation with
respect to composability between entity
and role or what's called syntax and
sematics right the en in the role so
while roles encoded by hipocampal cical
interactions can certainly be spatial
they can also be
non-spatial and even nonspatial and non-
ukian potentially involving arbitrary
roles such as a ve or what we would call
right uh some kind of event
anchor so the entity role bindings
currently explored empirically in humans
are limited to things like which
position and which sequence but if other
roles like if then else can be encoded
in a similar way then replay May form a
viable candidate um for a
neurophysiological mechanism
implementing symbolic computation so
this compositional nature of Replay is
implemented via our friend Thea gamma
coupling um mirroring closely the
present assumptions of lexical feature
sequencing and basic semantic
compositionality being complemented via
the same Dynamics and high gam activity
and there's a nice paper recently by
Nina kazanina and dve poel that explore
very similar Notions they kind of argue
that a lot of the neural mechanisms
already known to be found in hippocampus
could be used for symbolic language of
thought in language uh language of
thought meaning the kind of classical
fodorian notion um so you know a lot of
the a lot of what's already known
outside of language about the
neurobiological infrastructure for
things like navigation could be utilized
and exploited by the language system in
order to achieve its goals of um
composable functions compositionality
and basic structure building so that's
again once again it's an empirical
question these are all empirical
questions but I think the you know the
purpose of this paper which is a purely
theoretical paper is to kind of
negotiate through this terrain and see
which candidates are more feasible more
likely Etc and I think this this
candidate in particular I'm not the only
one who thinks this is a very you know
viable candidate for grounding some of
the
initial again the stress is initial for
me it's initial it's it's just that
initial phase of uh the early phase of
merge the basic set formation process
the theic gam stage potentially not the
uh you know human specific structure
building stuff that I mentioned earlier
to do with the structural inferences um
that involve uh other mechanisms that I
mentioned but at least in some aspects
of language electrical search electrical
access uh you know morphologic
morphologically complex word binding and
so on it's likely that these things are
potentially use as
well okay um and then in terms of so
memory transfer this is a an important
um concept that's been raised recently
by working by bring at Arland and El
Miller um this is just this section just
very briefly reviews um how we might
transfer memories across cortex which
kind of might look a little bit like
transferring syntactic structures into
workspace or transferring um stored
items into a separate kind of
consolidation or monitoring workspace um
there's some kind of potential for for
research in this
domain and then turning to Alpha Beta
Dynamics this is an interesting topic U
that I mentioned briefly earlier to do
with how the you know the the the role
of these oscillations that are outside
the main code space that I've already
mentioned right I've already mentioned
I've delimited my code space what about
the uh the role of Alpha and beta I
mentioned it briefly but it's a it's
kind of a quite an important role given
that they are quite dominant that
they're very prominently found in um
inter cranial and and extracranial
Research into language so um just
focusing on syntactic memory there's a
recent paper G Cel which supports a role
for beta in syntactic identity just
being sensitive to the identity of of a
sentence the type of category that you
afford it uh these authors investigated
speech memory representations using
interanal recordings in the left paryan
cortex during delayed sentence
reproduction in patients undergoing
awake tumor surgery uh based on the
memory performance of patients they
found that the phase of front temporal
beta represents sentence identity in
working memory uh the notion of
sentential identity presupposes a
labeled or categorized structure like a
verb phrase uh seemingly represented
partially by front to temporal beta and
converging with other literature beta
may represent aspects of the global
cognitive set going Beyond syntax
specific information to include
conceptual and statistical information
again I I mentioned the role of beta in
syntactic anticipation syntactic
prediction the kind of statistics of
language and I think that that has an
important role to play here again um
inter Cranium recordings by y truly um
of auditory language comprehension also
implicate frontal uh Alpha and beta
power in phrase prediction and
anticipation they kind of Mark the
moment of potential anticipation of of a
licensed phrase uh another paper found
that both uh Theta and Gamma are
sensitive to syllable rate but only bet
power is modulated by comprehension
rates so comprehension obviously implies
you know semantics and syntax rather
than just
syllables um and over the past decade in
fact a little bit longer than that over
the past 15 years or so there's been a
debate about whether beta power effects
during sentence comprehension reflect
syntactic computations or instead
reflect maintenance or set updating um
and to Briefly summarize the most
current results it appears that the
latter maintenance hypothesis is most
well supported um so I'm therefore going
to you know put further discussion of
this to one side um but the basic role
of it in in maintenance in terms of just
you know continuing aiding with the
assisting in some way of maintaining the
set of uh Genera and sustained cognitive
representations not necessarily being
sensitive to the properties of this set
not being sensitive to the particular
syntactic Identity or the category of
the syntax so even the category of the
semantics or the features of the
semantics but at least being involved in
coordinating neural resources available
neural resources to help with the
sustaining of that memory in work in in
in a current space again this is very
domain general not specific to language
which is why I think it's you know you
don't you find fewer of the um language
specific syntax semantics sensitivities
um even though it's in comprehension as
I mentioned comprehension means
everything it's just like you know
processing a sentence means loads of
things it doesn't mean specifically
syntax specifically language specific
stuff it just means you know when you
when you when you process a sentence you
do all sorts of things um so I think
it's most likely that it's involved in
these kind of more domain general
maintenance processes um and then in
parietal cortex Alpha enhancement seems
to index syntactic working memory
demands uh much like the regulation of
gamma by Alpha in control and attention
mechanisms that I mentioned earlier
varial cortex may play an important role
in memory and complexity such as low
frequency rhythms originating in lateral
or medial partic cortex regulate the
activity of gamma encoded operations in
lateral temporal cortex and single unit
or assembly encoded are in medial
temporal or inferior cortex that's a
more kind of specific
proposal um and another like likely site
of syntactic working memory uh is in PR
frontal sulcus for reasons cited in this
paragraph it's very heavily involved in
all sorts of interesting uh semantic
integration processes um and and
then yes as as I mentioned um the kind
of bringing this model to a kind of
conclusion um these assumptions take
place all within the context of the of
the traveling wave framework right so
lower frequencies migrating across the
cortex particularly being relevant to
cases of um maintenance and storage so
traditional standing waves lead to
periods when all neurons in the network
are turned off whereas traveling waves
can ensure that sub portions of a
network remain consistently active
Direct compatible uh with the Mosaic
like architecture of posterior Temple
cortex in semantic integration I won't
explain that further but it's basically
the idea that you know within these um
small regions of Cortex like posterior
tempor cortex there's a very interesting
Patchwork of activity of little
satellites of um sensitivity to
different aspects of language even
though they're all generally sensitive
to language um within them there's kind
of more specialized regions um which is
not unlike what you find in brenal
Temple cortex for things like face and
place and uh other kinds of uh shape
perception uh kind of ventral visual
oipal cortex being having a kind of
tapestry of um you know a cellular a
cell specific sensitivity to different
representational
features
um so where exactly the the waves travel
to during phrase composition is again my
favorite phrase this is purely an
empirical question uh but some candidate
regions have been suggested work right
that's kind of where where we stand at
the moment that's where the field is at
the very moment
um so figure three here is the basic
processes of the Rose model um this kind
of just gives a general outline of how
Rose is hypothesized to be implemented
across the front of temporal language
Network um and at the bottom there's a
representation of the various frequency
interactions proposed to implement pH F
building so you have representations
category specific information being
encoded in
spikes with operations you have
Broadband gamma activity um initially I
hypothesize and PS s based on the in
cranial work that we've done but it
could be anywhere it could be in PG
could also be in portions of ifg
depending on the category potentially of
the of the phrase uh the the type of
structure you're generating that's an
open question very much open um in terms
of structure we have the low frequency
neural program driven by a temporal
cortex and then for encoding we have
these traveling waves that spatially
migrate
structure so this I also think that both
you know given what we know about the
speed of traveling waves I think it's
possible that um a lot of this stuff
feres um
up dorsal or vental Pathways across
anterior posterior to anterior temporal
cortex um and from posterior to anterior
um frontal cortex given the time scales
of sensitivity that we know exist
there okay this final section of the
paper talks about causal evidence um
which is increasingly becoming very
important these days in Neuroscience as
we've exhaustively mapped correlational
activity of loads of different
linguistic processes but we haven't
really got a good sense of which parts
of the brain are actually essential for
language so when you get regions X Y and
Z being activated you know region X
might be causally involved whereas
region Y and Z regions Y and Z might
just be activated or you know recruited
or implicated but not actually essential
for for the
function so this section is kind of
charts out some of the um ways of
exploring that empirically through
cortical stimulation mapping in the o or
in the AMU using TMS for example um or
joint TMS Meg studies that that's a
possibility there's also as a way you
can think of kind of uh providing
different portions of causal evidence
for these these models um and these
paragraphs here just kind of just review
um mostly nonlinguistic but also some
language research um into how people
have used these methods to disrupt
language in particular parts of the
brain um there's some more interesting
research disrupting particular phase
codes um trying to particular trying to
modulate either uh hypo or hyper exite
and particular osor Dynamics or pack
Dynamics in different parts of the brain
now that's a really good way to directly
test the causal involvement of a phase
code more generally because if you can
hyper excite a Theta Rhythm or hyp
excite a gamma Rhythm then that can
really screw up your potential your
facilitation of the coordination of
these electrical features and your your
attention and working memory and all the
rest of it so that's a great way to kind
of causally test um not just a brain
regions involvement but also a
particular brain like how a brain
regions
involed
okay um this section is much more
philosophical um if you guys play Elden
ring you might get the reference in this
in this in this section um but the the
point of this section is kind of
evaluate the the rose model to kind of
situate it in a large context uh to
relate it to existing models um uh in
the uh uh interrenal space and
extracranial space
too um so some of the important periods
um in this paper um so I've already
mentioned this paragraph I think to do
with how the how different parts of the
brain might be sensitive to different
passes so I'll skip that bit um this
paragraph here just outlines how the
very basic philosophy in row is that uh
misos scale neural organization can be
useful for brain function and that high
frequency gamma oscillations report
mechanisms and underlying communication
channels of neural
computation so neural oscillations
organize cortical activity to produce
computation uh and Rose Builds an
architecture for syntax that presupposes
this um some exciting prospects for
testing rows come in the form of multi-
Channel recordings with broad cical
access using B micro electr arrays etc
etc um and I just cite some more
technical examples there for people in
the field
um and then let's see what else do we
have here um yeah I've already mentioned
the inside out outside it well actually
I haven't mentioned that I've mentioned
Mars framework um but just very briefly
I think my model is um incompatible with
a bunch of recent ideas to do with um
encouraging people to explore the brain
from inside out so I'll just read this
paragraph and then maybe try and digest
it a little bit because it's it's it's
probably the most important
philosophical kind of grounding here
so brain models informed by
computational concerns will continue to
be needed in neurosciences yes that is
true in particular as we approach the
Advent of widespread availability of
single unit recordings and again one of
the anxieties I have with this paper is
that as you know linguists get their
hands on sophisticated neural recording
measures we really need to be careful
and quite conservative in knowing what
we can say with each of these measures
so if you give every Ling linguist on
the planet access to single unit
recordings and the human
brain you're going to get a lot of
papers making claims about um as I satti
Satur here neonian existential closing
neurons or um you know specific very
Niche kind of um saor types responsible
for all sorts of baroke and complicated
and not very cognitively plausible
linguistic constructs so I really wanted
to in this paper boil it down you know
decompose language into its primitive
components decompose at the
computational level and decompose at the
representational level that kind of goes
back to the 1980s kind of classical
framework of the computational
representational theory of Mind where
you have a series of fixed
representations units and fixed
computations or things that you can do
with those units this kind of actions
and objects right that's a basic
metaphysical human distinction between
things and processes actions uh objects
and all the rest of right nouns and
verbs um computations
representations um so I really wanted to
make it clear that
um you know next time you find yourself
with uh access to a single unit you know
uh data set you need to kind of have
sufficiently decomposed these levels to
make it kind of neurochemically and
neurobiologically plausible rather than
talking about the kind of more holtin
stuff that I that I mentioned earlier um
so it's kind of more it it's more of a
cautionary tale I guess um because I you
know other fields have gone this before
right um so for example um you know grid
cells right it's it's over the last
decade grid cells in um inal and Par
cample cortex were initially implicated
in um spatial navigation then it turns
out they're involved in auditory
navigation and then they're involved in
conceptual navigation it so in other
words they they end up just being
involved in navigation full stop just
all types of navigation um and I think a
similar kind of transition might happen
with when we get um an increasing number
of Publications about language in single
units you'll get a lot of people
initially saying oh well you know these
these units these specific cell types
are involved in X then it turns out
they're also involved in Y and Z and and
will ultimately end up being forced to
propose a more generic account for these
things which is why in in in my paper I
I try and you know focus it um I try and
appeal to as much generosity as I can
there's there's always going to be some
domain specificity because obiously
language has domain specific
representations and apparently domain
specific computations so we will need
some notion of domain specificity on
some level but the only question is like
where are you going to find that okay
I'm rambling a little bit so I'll just
I'll continue um so this outsid in
perspective has been critiqued recently
um uh duu um Baki um advocates for an an
Insider perspective on building neural
models of cognition and considers the
classical Marian framework a purely
outside imp perspective yet Mah himself
stressed that the three levels should be
investigated in parallel not necessarily
prioritizing any given level so this is
a balancing app there right uh too much
outside in and you're going to get these
neonian neurons too much inside out and
you're going to be told that Linguistics
departments need to shut down right so
regardless of your own philosophical
bent I think single unit and other types
of interanal recordings are plainly the
most direct and reliable means to
further test and refine rows in
particular given recent independent
assessments and critiques of bold activ
but you know the basic message here is
that um a purely Insider perspective is
when people will say well what's called
Data driven science or datadriven
Neuroscience right where you say well
let's just um do a bunch of
sophisticated statistical analyses on
our single unit data and see what kind
of emerges um let's just see that let's
just hope that language will just arise
somehow without any ideological
presuppositions or any kind of biases
first of all it's impossible I think for
any human being to do that even if they
tell themselves they're doing it you're
always going to be delivering some
biases you're always going to be
bringing some philosophy of science or
philosophy of mind to the table whether
or not you like it or not um on the
other hand you have the completely um
outsid imp
perspective which I'm also very much
against so the outside in perspective
would say let's you know everything that
everything that linguist say is
Bible um all these theories of D
movement and Pie piping and all the rest
of it they are literally what the brain
cares about and we have to find that in
the brain we have to keep our fixed
theories of high Ro cognition and just
look at the brain and expect the brain
to care about everything we care about
we expect the brain to be sensitive to
all the stuff that we as linguists care
about and the problem of science is that
you know there's always a negotiation
going on there's always a kind of deal
that needs to be made um so you know one
of our former presidents talked about
the art of the deal in this case the art
of the deal in this case is figuring out
uh how much um Linguistics you need to
to hold on to and stay true to and how
much you need to let go of and how much
you need to say the brain doesn't care
about this you know it only cares about
this but not that H my own so my own
feeling is that the brain excuse me the
brain does genuinely care about some
aspects of language domain specific or
or otherwise namely the representational
feature types and also this business of
marriage and labeling that I mentioned
the basic computations I think the brain
does genuinely care about that it
probably doesn't care about all the
other stuff that link talk about um but
it can be characterized at some kind of
more EP epiphenomenal level I guess as
some kind of Imaging phenomenon we can
talk about the philosophical details you
know in other kind of uh Frameworks if
you like but that's the kind of I think
way to go about I think it's much too
harsh and arrogant to just completely
abandon all of the insights of
contemporary Linguistics just because we
have sophisticated Neuroscience I think
some holding on to some insights from
Linguistics will be essential to direct
and test and you know refine our data
driven science too um so I think what
Baki talks about in his book is I think
misleading and kind of a you know
unhelpful Division I think it's not I
don't like to talk about inside out or
outside in I think it's kind of just you
have a balancing act between both right
it's you have to just negotiate when
it's appropriate to use computational
levels and when it's appropriate to use
implementational level theories um okay
so that takes care of that um I'll skip
over this bit
here
um yes so this this this gets into what
I mentioned I I mentioned this maybe a
little bit briefly um but it's very
common to object to these kinds of
proposals of the kind I mentioned in
Rose as a kind of crude form of direct
mapping right or isomorphism and I'm so
some people listening to me right now
might think well you're kind of a
hypocrite because you're doing exactly
what you're critiquing Baki we're doing
right I'm complaining that Baki is just
no sorry I'm complaining that these
outside in people are just imposing
their linguistic theory on the brain and
I'm saying you shouldn't do that at the
same time though the whole point of the
Rose model is to directly map on what
different types of linguistic structure
onto the brain so a complete niist or
you know might say well the brain really
doesn't care about any of these
structures the brain really doesn't care
about um Atomic features lecal items
feature bundles phrases uh you know sets
of sets of sets and all the rest of it
now that might indeed be true that's
totally possible um I think it's
unlikely given that the um you know
um the specific responses that we've
seen at different levels of linguistic
complexity the kind of sociable scales
of sensitivity you can see at different
neuro complexity scales that I mentioned
here um but so you know the rose model
is essentially invoking a direct mapping
in some way a kind of onetoone um
correspondence between a scale of
linguistic complex X and a neural
mechanism Y and you kind of you know you
you find you follow that all the way up
until you get to the um ultim the
highest level of nesting that you get
with the Delta Theta complex all the way
down to the AL PE cing that I
mentioned earlier
right okay um so some people might say
that's a problem uh Rose continues this
crude tradition haha and by establishing
an even more explicit isomorphism
between system level complexity and
syntactic complexity so for example
cells and Sy actic features versus
global coherence and phas structure on
the other hand um alternative accounts
that build syntactic operations into
neural systems of diverging levels of
structural complexity have not been
forthcoming by the way so if they do
forth come then we can test them as well
um but would also naturally be required
to establish any kind of adversarial
collaborations and experimental testing
of the models um so through this it
would be possible to pit different
candidate neural mechanism for syntax
against one another and compare effect
sizes across studies to see which mechan
Mech ISM either from Rose or some other
model best explains real time direct
political effects of language processing
so that's a nice way to directly test
the rose model but I also want to
emphasize here that as far as I know the
the rose model is the only model of
syntax um n neurobiological model of
syntax that takes seriously this whole
notion of the fact that the brain
genuinely exhibits distinct levels of
neural complexity organization and
scales of complexity and also take
seriously the fact that not all neural
recording meeses just measure the same
thing right um single units up to Utah
up to SGS up to EOG up to Meg up to scal
Peg um these are very different beasts
and they record very different things um
it's easy and convenient and maybe
comforting just to say well the kind of
signal that we see in scalp RP responses
and delta waves are probably just some
kind of summated you know phase reset of
whatever's going on at the spike level
um on on some level of description
that's
true however it doesn't help with
building model of syntax in the brain
that's just kind of dismissal so my
appeal here is to kind of ground it more
concretely in different levels of
analysis and so far you know all the
other models of syntax in the brain as
I've said are localizationist as opposed
to kind of algorithmic or that's why the
the subtitle of this paper is a
neurocomputational architecture because
it's a neurocomputational architecture
and it is very much an architecture
there's within the row architecture you
can imagine three or four or five you
know very different specific theories of
or models from the architecture so you
know it's very much an architecture and
within this paper I propose my own
specific theories at each level but the
AR the scale of the architecture scaling
from the spike yeah Spike of PE coupling
up to pack up to traveling waves that's
the architecture but so within the
architecture you could maybe reframe
some of these things as long as the the
mechanistic relations between R to O to
S to e are maintained that's the kind of
General framework here
um and then going back to metaphysics
for a moment um Rose is also sympathetic
to recent moves in philosophy of biology
to view a range of biological constructs
as processes rather than
objects Rose is built entirely from
neurocomputational mechanisms that are
already known to Subs of clusters of
generic perceptual and cognitive
operations right I'm not invoking any
new neural mechanisms I'm not I'm not
proposing a new kind of you know microt
tribal quantum you know computational
mechanism to explain all this I'm being
very very conservative and just using
literally stuff that's been published in
the most you know high impact serious
scientific journals uh which which been
has been afforded textbook level
treatments at every level so all of
these mechanisms have been given serious
textbook treatment the only difference
here is that I'm migrating some of these
concerns over to the linguistic domain
um for with with various different
motivations across the levels um
um okay and then turning slightly
further um so yeah another nice Point
here made in the nature neuro paper by
Nina kazanina and Alexandra Tano and
current theor is that model hierarchal
stri building via low frequency Dynamics
correlates some neural measure with
attributes of a hierarchical syntactic
structure and thus concern the outcome
of syntactic structure construction so
this is a critique of those Meg and EG
studies that show this low frequency
Delta entrainment or Peak response at
moments of syntax it's a very legitimate
critique but by initiating certain
syntactic structure building at the
cellular R level and accounting for how
these output um how these output low
frequeny responses at the SN levels the
rose architecture goes beyond these
other accounts that are more closely
tied to the output of structure building
so and again even in the Rose
architecture this is correct that the uh
these low frequency Delta speaks are
indeed the output of the structure
building I'm not denying that I'm not
saying they're the input you know
they're not some kind of intermediary
response kazina and tabana are
completely correct they do they do
reflect some kind of um
readout the final stage of the syntactic
structure building process um to kind of
wrap up or even monitoring stage and for
me it's part of the um structure to
encoding phase and but at least the
early stages of syntax at the RN levels
are definitely at this this kind of
Spike level and High gam activity
level
okay um yes and then again open
questions remain about how to ground
this in more neurochemically explicit
models I haven't talked much about
neurochemistry uh some of my earlier
papers in 2015 2016 tried to take
neurochemical Frameworks much more
seriously and I have more of a like
mathematically rigorous framework into
uh negotiating particular low frequency
Dynamics and but in this paper I'm just
kind of leaving that to one side for now
because the paper's already you know way
too long u and I'm just focusing on the
kind of Architectural Components that's
something to be focused on at a later
stage
okay um yes yes yes okay so turning to
the conclusion um you know I've
mentioned a few times that this the rose
architecture really does come in
response to the absence of phase coding
models in language there's been a lot of
phase coding responses um or phase
weighted um you know entrainment and low
responses empirically documented they've
been empirically documented but in terms
of the actual theoretical you know
summary that's kind of been lacking so
that's my main motivation um and many
researchers who have kept the Frameworks
emerging purely from extrenal you know
Meg derived event related fields or scal
related potentials or fmri responses Etc
these guys have begun to to lose
Hope they've begun to lose hope in in
the prospect of of of finding syntax in
the brain so for example Lena pinin
who's probably you know the world's most
respected neurobiologist of syntax uh
she's written that the Neuroscience of
language field has long assumed that our
brains build syntactic structure during
language processing today it's
reasonable to question this assumption
and she's you know she's totally right
and uh motivated to say that because
she's summarizing research from extra
mostly extal stuff like Meg and FM and
she's definitely right that if you just
focus on that research it seems pretty
hopeless um I think the lack of space
tempal the lack of high spatial temperal
resolution in these methods explains the
absence and that's kind of one of the
implications of this paper um this paper
is essentially indirectly critiquing
that that field so so pilin you know
reasonably speculates that based on the
evidence reviewed in her article
something like merge might not be an
obvious neural
operation um or alternatively it might
not be found in presently exploded neur
signals um in fact she has this nice
distinction between um syntax as
knowledge and semantics is process where
in um you know neural recordings across
all
methodologies finding signatures of
semantics is very easy because semantics
is very energetically costly um the
number of words and possible Concepts
you can combine at any given moment is
really kind of astonishing you know the
number of different feature spaces you
can talk you can you can talk about
green horses made from licorice that
ride to Mars next Tuesday you can talk
about all sorts of surreal St right so
semantics is very um unpredictable um it
it it calls upon a wide range of cross
qual representational features what
about
syntax syntax is very different because
syntax is is syntax is just merge that's
it you just build you just you put two
things together and then you label it so
that's it that there's no diff there's
no novelty there every time you you you
build a phrase you do it in the same way
way you build a you build a phrased
architecture you label it you stack it
into a workspace you label that you ship
it off uh to an interpretation and
procedure um that's it that that's all
of syntax and you do it again and again
and again uh you don't have a different
merge process on Tuesday as you did on
Friday but semantics is like I said
there's a big difference here between
the space of semantics and the space of
syntax the space of syntax is just this
merge this one operation so it's no
surpris that it's been very difficult
for scientists to find neural signatures
of of of syntax syntax specific
responses because it's like we do it so
reflexively and so trivially and we've
been doing it you know since infancy
maybe even before infancy um depending
on which language acquisition theorist
you believe in um whereas semantics were
constantly changing it you know it it
takes years and years and years for us
to really build our our full repertoire
of developed semantics which syntax once
you've built a phrase you've built a
phrase that's it You' you've got all the
syntax the only thing that you can go
beyond that is you know kind of
performance aspects like how complex a
sentence you can construct right can you
read Shakespeare can you read Joyce you
know can you read David Foster Wallace
these that's that's a very different
question but that's a question about
performance it's a question about like
working memory attention you know all
those sorts of things when it come the
actual basic component of syntax is just
m so I think pinin is right that you
know maybe she's not I don't think she's
right that you know meres knowledge and
semantics is process I think they're
both process and they're also both
knowledge too um but in terms of why
it's been difficult for people to find a
signal reliably that it's because that's
all the rest to syntax whereas of
semantics you're going to get a very
reliable uh very serious uh neural
energetic cost involved in in processing
sentences so and in fact in our lab in
our interanal recordings for our
epilepsy patients all the response all
the most reliable responses you see are
clearly with uh you know meaningful
sentences as opposed to um you know
semantically impoverished sentences that
have a good syntax because it's it's
just difficult to really disentangle
those things um but that leads to into
some some other questions that I won't
get into because that's that'll take us
to a different topic um but so you know
I guess I've tried to what I've tried to
do with this paper is that with rose I
think I've at least provided some
candidate neuros signals and they do
exist there's plenty of candid neur
signals some very good ones um and that
can you can be readily investigated in
this manner so um yeah I think that kind
of settles that issue at least for me um
so under rows there's basically no sense
to be made out of claims that syntax
lies in one specific brain region I
talked about psts before being the real
sight of the initial phase of Mage but
in order to get to structural inferences
and then transferring up to a workspace
that's a global um phenomenon it
involves uh most likely uh you know
posterior temporal inferior frontal
coordination there's a nice paper in
pnas uh by Oscar
wner who's in our lab a postto in our
lab who showed very convincingly that um
building a coherent sentence structure
involves the coordination of overlapping
spal temporally overlapping but distinct
uh clusters in both posterior temporal
and inferior frontal cortex so it's not
just you know ifg versus PT it's kind of
like okay they're both involved but to
what extent
um some issues are a bit trickier to
discuss because you have to kind of
relate this to the legion literature
which kind of more reliably uh
implicates posterior temporal cortex
strongly and for my money if I were just
to you know contradict myself just a
little bit um I think the language
region is essentially posterior Superior
Temple Circus I think psts is basically
the language region with other things
coming online later due to um either
coupling or functional functional
coupling in coordination with psts psgs
will always be involved it's always the
Hub and these other regions like ifg and
ATL are involved and called upon for
performance reasons or to or reasons to
do with a downstage readout and
interpretation well psgs is the language
region um for me at least um so that's
kind of the seat uh of the Rose
localizationist Approach at least but
then the rest of the neural code spreads
far beyond that as I mentioned um I only
read one sentence of that paragraph
before before waffling um but I think I
pretty much already said that in many
ways um okay and then yeah we can think
about testability and all sorts of
different ways too uh to do with
separate out the category of the phrase
versus the semantics of the phrase
that's something to think about yeah
um okay and then in terms of um the
general roles in shaping information
processing the currently identified
frequency specific mechanisms seem to
align with an emerging consensus in the
field that slow frequencies control
input sampling Alpha and beta gate
information flow and high frequency
activity is controlled by slow rhythms
that's a very general kind of
neurocomputational you know framework
that's been explored in in the cognitive
neurosciences um and then moving beyond
this a newly emerging focus on brain
criticality and how this concept might
relate to brain rhythms provides
exciting revenues for future work in
theoretical neur Linguistics so that's a
cool concept too um and in fact there's
some really good work um exploring how
in some of my early papers I talked
about uh what's called globularity which
is this concept of um the fact that the
human brain is uniquely um almost
spherical relative to other primates
it's not completely spherical obviously
um but a lot of cognitive abnormalities
come with a brain shape reorganization
um and the fact that the human brain is
kind of more globular than our ancestors
has been used to motivate a lot by a lot
of serious anthropologists and also
neurobiologist ologists uh this idea
that the human brain is kind of uniquely
efficiently wired in some way to
facilitate cross cortical and also
subcortical um information integration
um so I think there's something to be
said there to do with um you know an
evolutionary change in brain shape
globular brain shape would have
naturally facilitated different paths
for these traveling waves to move across
right um different patches of Cortex can
can communicate with each other and in
fact we know from work by people like L
falky that the basic computational kind
of uh contribution of language is to
provide a kind of universal currency for
different um conceptual domains to talk
to each other excuse me so language is
basically giving you you know you have
then your number sense your sense of
morality your sense of intuitive physics
intuitive geometry uh intuitive botony
know what there's all sorts of different
domains in the psychology literature
concerning how human beings have been
inative modules for understanding
reality and constructing a g to model of
the
world um language seems to uniquely
allow us to conduct transactions between
these domains whereas in non-human
primates they may not be encapsulated
exactly but they are much more kind of
atomized um the modules you know
nonhuman primates have most of these
modules for sure no doubt maybe all of
them but they don't have a way of um
conducting transactions between them
whereas of humans we can talk about you
know um a large number of you know funny
green colorful heavy balloons or
whatever right we can combine different
conceptual categories together and
number sense morality you know um uh
different geometrical constructions
emotional constructions we can use
language to access all of these
different cognitive constructions now
even more interestingly there's some you
know it the if you look at the kind of
syntax of natural language there's been
some really interesting work by people
at qu University and and other
university showing that if you take the
list of human semantic Concepts and the
list of human kind of you know
electrical items and
features there's a lot of overlap in
terms of like uh event structure and
agent um uh uh processes and and and
features but there's also some
nonoverlap so there's certain um uh
concern the certain Notions like worry
or concern for example that are not
morphologically marked in any language
whereas things like you know
trustfulness or or or belief and uh you
know things like that are are marked in
by by by words and language so there are
certain um conceptual features that are
very readily found across to the world's
languages and have certain morphological
inflections for or or features for but
there are also certain epistemic Notions
or Notions pertaining to knowledge and
truth and so on um that are not readily
morphologically marked so that suggests
that there are certain parts of the
brain certain critical modules that the
language system does connect with and
does functionally speak to and interact
with but there are other cognitive or
perceptual modules that it does not
speak to that it's more isolated wrong
so that's kind of a potential way to
kind of think about ways to relate the
kind of neurobiological infrastructure
with the kind of Behavioral linguistic
kind of
phenomenon okay
um so yeah and then just to conclude the
more kind of philosophical foundations
of Rose um are also in line with
research documenting a rich array of in
capacities utilized during language
acquisition in the unit which can
distinguish distinct phones detect word
boundaries lay words and so on um I'm
kind of really invoking a very rich kind
of array of um innate capacities so uh
currently due to the lack of consensus
regarding how to ground syntatic comor
anality in the brain researchers enjoy
many degrees of freedom When selecting
from their preferred linguistic Theory
processing Theory the algorithm and
neurological framework the
implementational framework um so I hope
that Rose basically allows us to um you
know fairly constraint this landscape to
narrow the space of likely candidate
neuro mechanisms for syntactic stru
building it's really all about figuring
out what are the what are the most
likely mechanisms that we're going to
find um natural language syntax in the
brain which parts of the brain are going
to be sensitive to it and which really
index that process on some level um so
yeah I think I guess I should probably
leave it there and conclude it but um
yeah that's pretty much the whole
model thank you for the massively
informative overview and the research
agenda do you want to stay happy to stay
for a bit longer for sure yeah yeah
happy to chat all right well there's so
many places to join for people who are
watching live maybe we'll have a few
minutes to ask
question
wow yeah if you have any questions or
comments or thoughts I mean I I can I
can I can sit here all day and just talk
forever about this stuff but I probably
shouldn't all right I have uh a handful
let's do some short answers and just
some general because on the evidence and
on the specific brain regions and
specific time scales you've made that
abundantly clear so going to ask some
alternate questions so
okay how do we study these densely woven
cognitive
phenomena without how do we hold that
tension without just resorting simply
only always to holism or
reductionism you kind of talked about
that with the inside out and outside in
views but how can
we approach a different cognitive system
maybe not the human brain and language
where even the relationships amongst the
different phenomena might
be themselves not
known um okay I see you mean so if
there's some kind of you mean a human
specific cognitive process that is not
language and yeah if you want pull out a
different thing or study a different
system what kind of account are we
looking for how are we going to know
we're on the path that's not being just
massively misleading and so on no no
that's a good question um so I think I
think so the rose architecture I think
is is partially applicable to lots of
different cognitive domains I think for
attention and working memory uh you know
face perception Al faction they all
involve something at the r to O Level
the coordination of Spike timing and the
um the realization of some kind of
centry motor Transformations at the
Broadband gamma level the the thing
where we take over is really at the S
level where you get the uh particular
type of low frequency coordination that
seems to be specific for language but
it's you know language is not the only
thing that recruits um you know uh low
frequency um illary phase codes to
conduct the orchestra of you know
representations that need to be
externalized or interpreted um so I
think the
it it's it's transferable in many ways
the real um
testable uh issue will be to do with
whether or not these um you know whether
or not I'm correct that these different
levels of linguistic scripture are found
only at these levels or maybe they're
found across all of them um so for
example if effects of syntax specific
responses can be found truly at the r
the O the S and the E scales that I've
mentioned that muddies the waters
because it means that um the you know
the brain at every scale across all
areas cares about the most Niche
specific issues in in syntax we might
have to turn ultimately to um State
space architectures u which I suspect
will be used to supplement rows at least
at the at the um the uh the s& levels I
think in terms of you'll have like um
different um abtract States being
coordinated across Network nodes um
rather than the kind of which is you
know similar to what I mentioned to with
traveling wave just a more kind of
global interactional process but for a
very different mathematical grounding
it'll have a very different mathematical
grounding um so but I think um I don't
know I'm not sure if I'm answering your
question well but I I think I think in
terms of transferring it to to other
domains that are that could be explored
um it's really about um you know trying
to find trying to find a prediction of
like I will I need to use a particular
methodology I need to use a particular
experimental Paradigm to find effects
that should only be found at this
particular neural resolution and in this
respect it's no different from the rest
of the cognitive Sciences because in
working memory and attention and
navigation that's exactly what these
guys have done for decades uh
Linguistics as usual is you know the
last person to the party um we are
usually linguists are usually the last
in COG Neuroscience to kind of you know
pick up the developing tools in the in
the field and apply them um so and
that's fine you know there's nothing
wrong with that it turn I think the
reason is because human language is the
most complex cognitive process that we
have it requires a lot of the weeds to
be sorted out before we have to figure
out how working memory Works how
attention Works how Vision Works before
we can even worry about language um
because all of them kind of presuppose
and and require that right at some level
so I think it's natural for language to
be saved until last right save the best
of last for sure no doubt um but I think
it's also it makes it um it's also the
case that neural linguists have not
always taken the lessons that previous
Fields have learned as seriously and we
often end up making the same mistakes so
when we got scal scal pegs for the first
time or or fmri we made a lot of the
same mistakes um that the uh memory guys
did or the navigation guys did
um and I think my own fear you know in
writing this paper is that the reason
why I wrote this is mainly because you
know I see it in the last few months I
say in the last year or so um ctive
neuroscientists getting their hands on
very Advanced recording techniques but
not really knowing what to make of it
again this very aggressive very but also
very contemporary and very Progressive
kind of So-Cal Progressive Viewpoint of
know data driven science where you just
kind of let the data speak for itself
and uh allow the statistics of your uh
you know or do some kind of machine
learning um on on your kind of on your
data and expect that to kind of feed
into an explanation for language a lot
of those techniques um also discourage
this kind of theoretical reflection um
and if you look at people like KL
friston you know he spends most of his
time he's the world's most influential
neuroscientist he spends most of his
time just doing theoretical Neuroscience
because it's that's that that's really
where we're at these days in a lot of
these fields it's about consolidation
interpretation a lot of the a lot of the
um I mean I was surprised when I when I
started writing this paper I was
surprised that a lot of the clues and
answers to this puzzle of how syntax is
implanted in the brain are kind of
already out there they just haven't been
very you know uh the dots haven't been
connected the uh the principled
relations and logical relations between
different findings and different um you
know recording methodologies um and the
kind of more principal relations between
them haven't been established yet or
haven't been fig out um and I think
there's often a push and a desire to
just you know do another experiment uh
you know get funding to do more and more
experiments and collect more data and do
more analysis that's obvious essential I
I do that as my day as my day job um but
outside of my day job I think it's it's
also important to spend some time you
know thinking about how to thinking more
carefully about this so that you don't
need to do any more experiments for a
while um so you or at least so you know
that you know when you do your
experiments you know the the landscape
better um and you don't end up making
the same mistakes that other people do
um but really it's it goes back to this
issue of kind of cost cost benefit like
you know how do you how do you kind of
weigh up the um the pros of collecting
more data with the um you know the the
foreseeable benefits but the whole
notion of foreseeable benefits empirical
foresee foreseeable benefits really
presupposes and needs this framework of
what the benefits are likely to be if
the benefits are just I'm going to just
let the data speak for itself and get a
bunch of different you know machine
learning um or llm architectures to kind
of figure out the story for me you're
probably going to be disappointed um
whereas if you take a step back and
think about a more principled
architectural approach like think about
the brain the way an engineer it would
um and figure out like which level is
going to be best served for a different
a particular cognitive process that's
that's the basic mindset behind behind
this model it's about figuring out like
you know which scale of operation is
going to be most helpful for
you great well on that kind of research
program scale the compass rose it's a
great model um I was curious about a few
other settings for speech like listening
to a video or recording at a different
speed than 1ex or watching subtitles or
just the idea of reading and whether
there was some kind of a um
clean handoff between one sentence is
heard and then one is read then one is
heard is it beyond the sensory modality
by what stage or what elements that are
extra lexemic like Pro and timing and so
on play into for example speech as
opposed to writing where there's
formatting and italics and so on yeah no
that's a great question so um there's a
there's an there's there's an unanswered
question at the moment
which is to do with the bottleneck of
reading or speech process well speech
processing not too much but definitely
for reading um we don't really know that
much about the bottleneck like how fast
you can read um so the rose model talks
about Delta rhythms it talks about the
rhythms these are very slow waves if you
ever tried speed reading it becomes very
clear straight away that human beings
can read very
quickly um so if you if you you know
code in mat lab or or python some kind
of RSVP style um you know uh textbook
where you can just like have one word
flashing on the screen at a time and set
it to different rates if you have it you
know 50 500 milliseconds away no problem
it turns out you can go way faster up to
like you know 15 20 words a second and
you can still get
interpretability um you you'll be
surprised if if you try it you'll be
very surprised about how fast you can
actually read um so you might think that
poses a problem for the rose
architecture I don't think it does I can
get to that after I've answer your
question it doesn't POS a problem at all
um but so that's that's a good question
so we know that there are certain parts
of the brain that do um in the vental
temporal cortex um which is the Lower
Side of the UND side of of the temporal
low they are responsible for um fun
transforming visual information into
orthographic information and in fact the
work of Oscar wol now in my lab he's
done the most impressive work on this by
far and Inter very Exquisite like inter
cranial recordings of how human beings
um in fact his whole research is on
reading so you should probably
definitely read his work it's it's
basically about how the human brain
takes you know visual information and
then trans uh converts it into an
orthographic space a constrained
orthographic space a space in which you
know uh your mind I guess will be
sensitive to particular statistical
configurations of shapes like you know
this one's a letter this one's not a
letter so that takes place in a certain
part of the venal temporal cortex and
then maybe somewhere around there that
will due to endogenous um you know
processing um limitations probably not
to do with vision probably due to you
know some kind of uh next next stage
process to do with
interpretability and because as you know
we can read we can see based on card
rates and and all the rest the number of
like objects and things we can see in a
given second is is is is very large
indeed the human brain mostly filters
out you know most of its sensory
information every second just to kind of
focus on the stuff that's key to its G
model the stuff that's key to kind of um
you know minimizing the free energy of
it of it g model and keeping it kind of
sustained and um not changing the Status
Quo Etc but on the reading level uh we
know that um at that stage that's when
you get the Sentry motor what I call the
Sentry motor transformations in high gam
activity so that's where you get that
high gam activity being responsible and
sensitive to the mapping from that
visual information to the linguistic
information because obviously somehow
you've got to you see words on the
screen you see squiggles and lines
somehow you got to convert that into a
more abstract space so that all takes
place in the rental tempal cortex and
then you get some interesting
connectivity um and top down information
from being sent from frontal cortex back
to rental temporal to constrain and re
and and kind of
coordinate the that that bottleneck at
least that's one of the main theories
that that exists um I'm not an expert on
reading per se I'm not a vision
scientist but you know as far as I
understand that's the kind of
um the general framework is that there
is a part of the brain that's sensitive
to the St statistics but Al also the
symbology of orthographic information um
and we know that it takes place in very
short time scales um when it comes you
you asked a very interesting question
about the the kind of um you know Co the
kind of dual modality like when you're
watching a film you're listening it and
you're also reading sub Tiles at the
same time um that's a very tricky
question because um on the motor side we
know that you'll get auditory cortex
involvement and orthographic kind of
occipital temporal um involvement
engagement at the same time but somehow
they both have to converge on a single
interpretation right because we know
that um you can't comprehend things in
parallel you can't read two books at
once um or at least most people can't so
that means there's got to be a single
kind of interpretation procedure and a
single kind of semantic integration
process that is being instructed in a
form by different
modalities but when you think about it
that might sound difficult but it's
actually no different from when I use
hand gestures right now right so when I
use hand gestures I'm providing some
kind of extra modal information to you
uh it's obviously easier because this is
more hand drestes are usually kind of
pragmatically informative rather than
explicit propositional of course unless
you speak sign language um but with it's
it's still just a case of like different
sensory motor Transformations taking
place so that would still be at the at
the O Level that would still be at the
the O level of art it's still high gamma
Transformations that are then fed into a
more uniform um uh discrete and Abstract
syntactic inference being made there's
only one syntactic inference being made
about the meaning of the sentence but
it's being informed by multiple sites
now you do raise an interesting question
because that might that might be the
case it might be the case therefore that
this low frequeny Delta complex
therefore has to entrain and
functionally connect with multiple
cortical sites it might have to to speak
to aary Cortex but also Ral tempal
cortex if you're if you're gleaning
distinct um types of um if if if the
lower level lexal representations you're
getting are being sourced from auditory
then orthographic so for example if I
give you a sense and I CH and I get you
to hear the first word and then read the
second word and then hear read hear read
here or listen I should say listen read
listen read if you go between listening
and reading but you're still integrating
a single unific a unified structure we
know you can do that human beings can do
that so that tells you straight away
that you know it can be done um but the
question is how it's done like I said I
I suspect it's through this this dual
kind of tradeoff between Cent motor um
instructions being sent from auditory
cortex to to the same unified low
frequency program and then the visual
information too so that's that's
actually kind of a nice way to separate
out the distinction between you know
centry motor store
from the more abstract unified kind of
syntactic information that's being built
um and in fact you've just given me a
good idea for an experiment so thank you
cool yeah because language is so
linearized it's like being pulled
through a needle and then in the Cade
so-called speed reading but it's not
simply moving the linearization faster
speed reading can
leverage formatting and all these other
strategies like almost thinking through
other
Minds ways of reading and also having an
off center effect in visual system and
the way that that kind of
convolves the orthography versus in
listening you basically always want to
be listening more clearly because the
moment is the only time you're going to
hear it the active listening components
like you can't let it fly by but reading
you can you can take Cade strategies and
cognitive strategies that that you just
can't take and that's kind of this like
all at once versus one at a time
element there's actually there's a
framework in in pych linguistics called
the Now or Never bottleneck so the now
or never bottleneck refers to what
you're saying right in in Reading
there's no now or ever you can just take
your time with listening you're totally
right it's it's now or ever you have to
pay attention now and integrate or your
working memory is going to dissipate or
your attention is going to or your
phological Loop is going to Decay and
you're going to ask the person to repeat
themselves again and again um so it's a
very it's a very different performance
system and it's also very different from
Braille um when when you're touch using
touch and reading Braille when you're
gesturing and using sound language you
know language especially syntax truly is
a modal it's it's completely independent
of any modality
you know the Neuroscience of speech is
very different from the Neuroscience of
language the Neuroscience of of gesture
is very different from neurosci of
language your language is a more kind of
a modal abstract system that calls upon
these very various Sentry motor kind of
you know processes um which is what and
you know most people intuitively try and
ground language in a sentot kind of
context because that's natural of course
you know that that's how we access it
that's how we trigger it but obviously
you know most of most of our daily
language use is probably just thinking
to ourselves you know um using language
maybe on subconsciously using the using
the computational capacity that language
affords Us in non-linguistic ways
meaning to to construct hierarchical
structures of thought and planning and
uh you know and all the rest of it um in
in some kind of subconscious way uh
rather than explicitly saying I am
saying a sentence or even I am think
thinking a sentence in my head because
even when we think a sentence in our
head that's still just an internalized
form of externalization right so when
you think about in your head that's
still ex that's still externalization
it's just a different type of
externalization you're not externalizing
it with your mouth but you're still
putting it out into your own phological
Loop but that's not that's still
externalization internalization is truly
the subconscious process of generating
the syntactic inference which is done
rapidly reflexively uh you know
intuitively often without much thought
often meaning attention often without
much attention being directed to it and
any kind of conceptual implications
being made um so most of language use is
outside of the centory motor space I I
would argue maybe I'm wrong about that
but um this is a point that n trumpy has
made a lot and I think he's right about
this um you know a lot of the use of
like the daily use of the language
infrastructure um is AC like I said I
mentioned the universal currency
metaphor it's it's across these
different conceptual spaces um and it's
it's it's potentially represented very
redundantly across sparse neural codes
as I mentioned in in the Rose
architecture such that it survives brain
damage it survives all sorts of
different things um but um but it's
still keep it's is still crucial and you
got a lot of people like Rose M and
federo you know going showing work that
um you know damage to well you know
using Imaging research showing that um
the language network is not activated
during XYZ n linguistic cognitive tasks
or damage to the language network does
not damage you know XYZ nonlinguistic
tasks and that's all fine um but it's
really that's kind of a separate issue
from whether or not the more abstract
syntactic neural code that I that I've
presented in the paper is recruited on
some level by nonlinguistic uh resources
which I suspect it is um again another
empirical question for you right um but
I think that's a reasonable framework to
kind of assume at least
and
yeah cool one one I guess reflection on
that and then one last question
um you described language human
language as being a kind of psycho
technology with supporting architecture
and inculturation all these different
features that are are totally relevant
influence it that allows us to
articulate like the sense making an
action like when we look at figure 4.3
in the active inference textbook and we
have a basian graph that factorizes out
through the sparsity of just how things
are related like how the measurement of
the thermometer is related to the
temperature in the room how the
temperature in the room changes
fundamental concepts of place and time
where preferences fit into that what
this is about the semantics of this
variable whether it's kind of like a
central tendency or whether it's a
variance estimator like confidence which
is something that you brought up as like
a strong linguistic um utility so it's
kind of
like it has an element of just
being the geometry and topology of
thought and thinking and generative
modeling that has Ultra
mundane
everyday
uses because this generalized apparatus
really
does have utility pragmatic value in
communication so it can be used for the
most
referential um just one bump above
pointing at something and pointing at
something and grunting and pointing
something say look or look it's a like
you can keep going and but often what's
only needed is the first little bit
especially given a context and yet
there's this
open-ended
arbitrary State space
navigation element as well yet it's only
I just I think it's incredible how it's
laid out and how what you described with
a heavy emphasis on the
neurophysiological and the
computational comes into play with
active inference and the generalized
State spaces and all these Concepts so
that's just super exciting I guess my
sort of closing or or we can keep
talking or whatever but how do do you
see this relating to language learning
for first language and for not first
language learning yeah I I I I I totally
agree with what you said about the
active inference framework like I think
I think um you know linguistic semantics
and well you know syntactic structures
are a unique kind of inference that the
human brain has to make um the um I I I
see a lot of the the properties of Le
lexo semantics in human language as
being a unique type A Unique contributor
to the active inference framework and I
think it's it's a surprise to me that
more linguists haven't turned to active
inference to think about certain
properties of because it seems so
obvious it seems so compatible I've
tried to do it in some work um and I
think maybe some other people have too
potentially but it's um it's it's an
obvious kind of well I mean I cited the
Peter hag paper he cites that work too a
little bit um but no it's it's a very
promising way to to beue it um in terms
of um language learning and acquisition
that's a very very good question so in
the I mentioned at the beginning some of
the low frequency um Delta responses to
syntax all of that research is in adults
well all of it was until um some
researchers at Cambridge UK a few years
ago started to think okay well maybe is
this how children process language too
um or maybe is this how
is this where they process language in
the same regions it turns out if you
look at um teenagers and children and
you do the same kind of Lo um you know
SC scal b or maybe even Meg research I'm
not sure I can't remember I cited it in
my book um the uh low frequency
responses change over development in
terms of which um ranges are sensitive
to the periods of syntax so it's not
necessarily you know 1.3 HZ precisely
that entrains the syntax of course not
this gets back to the point number earli
about speed reading right it's all about
the flexible coordination and packaging
of representations um into a given
complex um again there I mentioned the
issue of trade-off between you know
number of representations you can chunk
and the F and the Fidelity of of the
representations you can have a few and
well represented in Gamma or a large
number and only a small number of spikes
uh per representation that's just kind
of you know that's a very general
framework that's been um supported in
the attention literature too it's not
just um my proposal so so that that that
poses the question if children and
teenagers show a different kind of you
low frequency phrase response how do we
deal with that um I don't have a clear
answer to that question I think the rose
architecture can very readily be
modified to that because it's not as if
you know for they'll still have the same
architecture they'll still have the same
you know R to O to S to e the particular
frequency band of Interest might shift
over development and in fact we know
from working memory and attention that
Theta Dynamics and Alpha Dynamics
definit and and beta Dynamics too do
change cross cortically over over
development um and these are
behaviorally relevant to things like um
development of working memory and
attentional resources that's that's been
very clearly studied and very well
studied too um so it's more like the
there's a more abstract code that simply
shifts its spatial temporal profile as
the brain gets older and then changes
more when we get even older so I have a
paper that going to um come out fairly
soon I hope to do with um aging and what
happens when we when our brains Decay
and we get old um there there's some
nent kind of research looking at the uh
language processing not at the behavior
level but in terms of the neur level the
neurobiology of um language processing
in older people um and how it might also
relate to you know breakdown of semantic
information access and things like that
and what are the potential correlates of
that so you can imagine very clearly
if you take the rose architecture which
components will be disrupted or modified
based on if it's a syntactic or a
conceptual or electrial kind of deficit
but you the the the isomorphism is as I
said very crude so you can you can
predict that very clearly and in fact
there's some research in that space that
I think is concordant with this which is
what I discuss in this newpaper um so um
it's it's you know it it like I said
it's a relevant architecture it's a very
difficult question about how the whole
brain um matures over time because you
know there's
certain aspects of knowledge that may
not be
represented um in ways that we currently
know how
to um you know uh detect or record um we
have the four or five measures main
measures that I mentioned in the paper
they're they're what we have right now
maybe there's a particular form of
neural encoding that it just goes Way
Beyond what we can physically provide in
the year 20 23 um I don't think there's
any reason to assume that we've reached
the limit of like decodability of neuros
signals and their complexity absolutely
not um so the learning process is is a
very mysterious one um so yeah I think I
think it's it's also it's also a really
good way to falsify a lot of this stuff
by the way it's a really good way just
to completely falsify and test a lot of
these proposals to do with the
architecture itself um and then
developing code over time as well so
yeah it's a very relevant concern the
the the best way to do it is um to get
Interra recordings in children uh that's
very difficult because so there's a uh
in Austin Texas there's a lab there has
that has that has these recordings and
and uses to um access to uh children
with epilepsy and they get these
children to you know Watch trailers of
films and listen to stories and things
like that and they do some interesting
language research uh in these kids
that's ex exceptionally rare data and
very very very useful data for answering
these questions I don't have access to
that data um and most of that research
has not been forthcoming yet there
there's been a couple of inter cranial
um papers in in in children and language
but it's it's fairly sparse fairly low
patient numbers and the types of
analyses have been too kind of remote
and and departed from this framework to
really test it but that would be the way
to test it get you know um electrodes
directly inside the brains of of of
children and potentially even younger I
think the youngest I've seen is about
four um but you know even by 4 years old
it's maybe too late to to chart the
actual full development of acquisition
of language because by that stage
they've already acquired syntax right if
you could get even I don't want to sound
like a mad scientist but like if if it's
possible ethical to to one day get
access to intercal recordings in very
young children then it would be possible
to chart this developmental process
especially if the children are in the
hospital for uh protracted periods and
in fact get some kind of I mentioned BCI
implants if they have some kind of
implanted device over time that would be
the most direct way to test this stuff
well not just test my theory but just
you know just just completely chart out
the full development of profile and the
evolution and the development of the
neurophysiological basis of of speech
processing and language processing um
but right now that's kind of as far as I
understand that's kind of like the
current landscape of of of where the
field is right
now wow well um you can have the last
word with any last thoughts but thank
you for this this amazing presentation
and I hope that if people are interested
that they can of course read the paper
and learn and reach out and maybe we can
have 64.2 when the time is right but
anything you'd like to kind of leave it
with yeah no thanks so much for having
me on man um it's been very it's been
great you've been great i' I've been
enjoyed it's been enjoyable just kind of
outlining my own Theory you know you
read your own paper over and over again
and you realize all the things that you
kind of misinterpreted or misread on
your face read through um in terms of
like phrasing and all the rest of it so
it's always good to to refresh these
things but no absolutely if people are
interested in in this stuff I'm always
open you know you can contact me via
email uh on on Twitter um very happy to
talk more absolutely So yeah thank you
for listening thank you for having me
thank you peace peace
peace